教   父
我相信美国
I believe in America.
美国使我发了财...
America has made my fortune...
而我以美国方式教养我的女儿
and I raised my daughter in the American fashion.
我给她自由
I give her freedom
但也告诉她永远不要有辱家门
but I taught her never to dishonor her family.
她交了个男友, 但不是意大利人
She found a boyfriend, Not an Italian.
她跟他去看电影, 深夜才回家
She went to the movies with him. She stayed out late.
我并没有责骂她
I didn't protest.
两个月前他与另一个男孩
Two months ago, he took her for a drive...
带她去兜风
with another boyfriend.
他们强灌她喝威士忌
They made her drink whiskey
然后他们想要占她的便宜
and then they tried to take advantage of her.
她反抗, 她保住了她的名节
She resisted, She kept her honor.
于是他们像对待动物一样打她
So they beat her like an animal.
当我赶到医院时, 她的鼻梁断了
When I went to the hospital, her nose was broken
她的下巴被打碎了
her jaw was shattered
用钢丝绑着才不会掉下来
held together by wire.
她痛得连眼泪都哭不出来了
She couldn't even weep because of the pain.
但我却哭了, 我为什么哭呢?
But I wept. Why did I weep?
她是我的生命之光
She was the light of my life.
漂亮的女孩
Beautiful girl.
现在她再也不会漂亮了
Now she will never be beautiful again.
不好意思
Sorry.
我... 我像个守法的美国人一样, 我去报警
I... I went to the police like a good American.
那两个男孩受到了审判
These two boys were brought to trial.
法官判处他们3年监禁, 但缓期执行
Ajudge sentence them to three years in prison,
and suspend their sentence.
缓期执行!
Suspended the sentence!
他们当天就被释放了!
They went free that very day!
我像个傻瓜似的站在法庭中
I stood in the courtroom like a fool.
而那两个混蛋, 竟朝着我笑
And those two bastard, they smiled at me.
于是我对我太太说
Then I said to my wife
"为求公道, 我们必须去找柯里昂阁下"
"For justice we must go to Don Corleone."
你为什么去找警察? 你为什么不先来找我?
Why did you go to the police? Why didn't you come to me first?
你想要我怎么样?
What do you want of me?
你尽管吩咐, 但求你一定要帮我个忙
Tell me anything, but do what I beg you to do.
帮什么忙?
What is that?
我要他们死
I want them dead.
那个我办不到
That I cannot do.
你要什么我都会给你
I'll give you anything you ask.
我们认识很多年了
We've known each other many years
但这是你第一次来找我帮忙
but this is the first time you ever
came to me for counsel or for help.
我不记得你上次邀请我到你家喝杯咖啡是什么时候了
I can't remember the last time that you invited me
to your house for a cup of coffee.
何况我太太还是你独生女的教母
Even though my wife is godmother to your only child.
我坦白说吧
But let's be frank.
你从来就不想要我的友谊
You never wanted my friendship.
而且你害怕欠我人情
And you were afraid to be in my debt.
我不想卷入是非
I didn't want to get into trouble.
我理解
I understand.
你在美国发了财
You found paradise in America.
生意做的不错, 生活过得很好
You had a good trade, made a good living.
有警察和法律保护你
Police protected you, and there were courts of law.
所以你不需要我这样的朋友
So you didn't need a friend like me.
现在你来找我, 你说...
But now you come to me and you say...
"柯里昂阁下, 请帮我主持公道"
"Don Corleone, give me justice."
但你对我一点尊重也没有
But you don't ask with respect.
你没有把我当朋友
You don't offer friendship.
你甚至不愿意喊我"教父"
You don't even think to call me "Godfather."
相反, 你在我女儿结婚的当天来到我家
Instead, you come into my house
on the day my daughter is to be married
用钱收买我为你杀人
and you ask me to do murder for money.
我请求你主持公道
I ask you for justice.
那不是公道. 你女儿还活着
That is not justice. Your daughter is still alive.
那么让他们像她一样受折磨
Let them must suffer then as she suffers.
我应该付你多少钱?
How much shall I pay you?
包纳萨拉, 包纳萨拉
Bonasera, Bonasera.
到底我做了什么让你这么不尊重我
What have I ever done to make you treat me so disrespectfully?
如果你以朋友的身份来找我
If you'd come to me in friendship
那么毁了你女儿的杂碎, 会在今天就遭受痛苦
then the scum that ruined your daughter
would be suffering this very day.
如果一个像你这样诚实的人碰巧树敌了
And if by chance, an honest man
like yourself should make enemies
那么他们也就是我的敌人
then they would become my enemies.
然后他们就会害怕你
And then they would fear you.
做我的朋友?
Be my friend?
教父
Godfather.
很好
Good.
有一天, 也许那一天永远不会到来
Someday, and that day may never come
我会叫你为我效劳
I'll call upon you to do a service for me.
但是, 嗯... 在那一天到来之前
But, uh... until that day,
收下这份公道作为我女儿的结婚礼物
accept this justice as a gift on my daughter's wedding day.
-谢谢, 教父  -别客气
-Grazie, Godfather. -Prego.
这件事交给克莱门扎
Give this to Clemenza.
我要用可靠的人... 头脑清醒的人
I want reliable people...
people that aren't going to be carried away.
我是说, 我们不是杀人犯, 下手别太重
I mean, we're not murderers,
in spite of what this undertaker says.
-迈克尔在哪儿? -什么? 别担心
-Where's Michael? -What? Don't worry.
没有迈克尔, 我们不能拍照
We're not taking the picture without Michael.
我们先不拍了
We're not taking it.
-怎么了, 桑尼?  -因为迈克尔
-What's the matter, Sonny? -It's Michael.
你好, 巴西尼阁下
Don Barzini.
你认得我儿子吧?
嘿, 保利! 让我喝点酒
Hey, Paulie! Let me have some wine.
-保利! 再来点酒  -对不起, 请吧
-Paulie! More wine. -Scusi, please.
你在舞池里棒极了, 你是舞蹈评委还是什么?
You look "terrif" on the floor.
What are you, a dance judge or something?
闪开吧, 到附近晃晃做好你的工作
Go take a walk around the neighborhood. Do your job.
嘿! 桑德拉, 拜托, 帮个忙. 看着点儿孩子, 别让他们狂奔, 好吗?
Hey, Sandra, come on. Do me a favor.
Watch the kids. Don't let 'em run wild, all right?
你看好你自己, 好吗?
Well, You watch yourself, all right?
2, 3万元. 小额钞票, 全是现金
Twenty or thirty grand. In small bills, cash.
全在那个小丝袋里
In that little silk purse.
如果这是我的婚礼, 我就发财了
If this was somebody else's wedding.
嘿, 保利! 我弄到两个加巴戈尔, 加巴哥和一个熏火腿
Hey, Paulie! I got two gobbagool, gabagol and a prosciutto.
你这个笨蛋!
Stupid jerk!
嘿, 怎么了?
Hey, what's the matter?
-我得回去工作了  -汤姆
-Have to go back to work. -Tom.
这是婚礼的一部分
It's part of the wedding.
没有西西里人能在女儿结婚那天拒绝任何请求
No Sicilian can refuse any request on his daughter's wedding day.
柯里昂阁下, 我很荣幸也很感激你邀请我来你家
Don Corleone, I am honored and grateful
that you have invited me to your home...
嘿!
Hey!
离开, 滚开这儿
Partire. Get outta here.
这是私人宴会. 快滚!
This is a private party. Go on!
你们干什么? 嘿, 这是我妹妹的婚礼
What is it? Hey, my sister's wedding.
该死的联邦调查局什么都不尊重
Goddamn FBI don't respect nothin'.
嘿! 过来, 过来, 过来, 过来!
Hey! Come here, come here, come here, come here!
...但最后, 他被假释以帮助美国的战争努力
...but towards the end, he was paroled to help with the American war effort
过去的6个月, 他一直在我的糕饼店做事
For the last six months, he's been working at my pastry shop.
纳佐林, 我的朋友, 我能为你做什么?
Nazorine, my friend, what can I do for you?
现在战争结束了
Now that the war is over
这个男孩, 恩佐, 他们想把他遣返回意大利
this boy, Enzo, they want to repatriate him back to Italy.
教父, 我有个女儿. 看, 她和恩佐...
Godfather, I have a daughter. See, she and Enzo...
你想要恩佐留在这个国家, 和你女儿结婚
You want Enzo to stay in this country,
and you want your daughter to be married.
-你什么都了解  -谢谢
-You understand everything. -Thank you.
哈根先生, 谢谢
Mr. Hagen. Thank you.
待会儿看看漂亮的结婚蛋糕... 我为你女儿做的
And wait till you see the beautiful wedding cake...
I made for your daughter.
这么高, 还有一对新人和天使...
Like this, with the bride and the groom and angel...
-这件事我该交给谁去办 -别给我们的同伴
-Who should I give this job to? -Not to our paisan.
把它交给另一个选区的犹太议员
Give it to a Jew congressman in another district.
名单上还有谁?
Who else is on the list?
嘿, 迈克尔, 你好吗?
-Hey, Michael. How are you?
-你好  -迈克尔
-Hello. -Michael.
卢卡·布拉西不在名单上, 但他想要见你
He's not on the list, but Luca Brasi wants to see you.
这个... 有这个必要吗?
Is this... Is this necessary?
他没想到会被邀请参加婚礼, 所以他想谢谢你
He didn't expect to be invited to the wedding,
so he wanted to thank you.
好吧
All right.
柯里昂阁下, 我很荣幸也很感激
Don Corleone, I am honored and grateful
你在你女儿结婚这天 邀请我到你家里做客
that you have invited me to your home
on the wedding day of your daughter.
愿他们的第一个孩子是男孩
And may their first child be a masculine child.
-唐... -迈克尔?  -柯里昂阁下...
-Don... -Michael? Don Corleone...
那边的那个人在自言自语
That man over there is talking to himself.
看到那边那个吓人的家伙了吗?
See that scary guy over there?
-他是个很吓人的家伙  -他是谁? 叫什么名字?
-He's a very scary guy. -Who is he? What's his name?
他叫卢卡·布拉西, 有时候帮我爸爸办事
His name is Luca Brasi. He helps my father out sometimes.
哦, 迈克尔,  等一下, 他过来了
Oh, Michael, Wait a minute. He's coming over here.
嘿! 迈克
Hey! Mike.
哦, 汤姆
Oh, Tom.
你看起来棒极了!
You look terrific!
我哥哥汤姆·哈根, 这是凯·亚当斯
My brother Tom Hagen. This is Kay Adams.
-你好吗?  -很高兴见到你
-How do you do? -Nice to meet you.
你父亲一直在找你
Your father's been asking for you.
-我会去的  -很高兴见到你  -很高兴见到你
-I'll be there. -Very nice to meet you. -Nice to meet you.
如果他是你哥哥, 为什么他有不同的名字?
If he's your brother, why does he have a different name?
哦, 我哥哥桑尼小时候, 在街上发现汤姆·哈根无家可归
Oh, when my brother Sonny was a kid...
he found Tom Hagen in the street, and he had no home
我爸爸收养了他
and so my father took him in
从那以后他就一直和我们在一起
and he's been with us ever since.
他是个好律师
He's a good lawyer.
不是西西里人, 但我想他会成为军师
Not a Sicilian, but I think he's gonna be consigliere.
-那是什么意思?  -那是...
-What's that? -That's a...
就像是个顾问, 参谋, 在家族中的地位非常重要
like a counselor, an advisor. Very important to the family.
你喜欢你的千层面吗?
You like your lasagna?
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone
我很荣幸也很感激
I am honored and grateful
你在你女儿结婚这天
that you have invited me to your daughter's wedding
邀请我参加你女儿的婚礼
on the day of your daughter's wedding.
我希望他们的第一个孩子是男孩
And I hope that their first child will be a masculine child.
我发誓永远忠诚
I pledge my ever-ending loyalty.
-这是给你女儿的新娘包  -谢谢你, 卢卡
-For your daughter's bridal purse.  -Thank you, Luca.
我最珍贵的朋友
My most valued friend.
柯里昂阁下, 我先告退了, 我知道你很忙
Don Corleone, I'm gonna leave you now,
because I know you are busy.
谢谢
Thank you.
柯里昂夫人!
Signora Corleone!
不! 不! 不!
No! No! No!
参议员考利对不能亲自来致歉
Senator Cauly apologized for not coming personally
他说你会谅解的
but said you'd understand.
还有一些法官也一样, 他们都送了礼物. 敬你
Also some of the judges. They've all sent gifts. To you.
外面是怎么回事?
What is that outside?
强尼! 强尼! 强尼!
Johnny! Johnny! Johnny!
我爱你
I love you.
他千里迢迢从加州赶来参加婚礼
He came all the way from California to come to the wedding.
我告诉过你他会来的
I told you he was going to come.
-已经2年了 -他可能又遇到麻烦了
-It's been two years. -He's probably in trouble again.
他是个好教子
He's a good godson.
强尼, 强尼! 唱首歌!
Johnny, Johnny! Sing a song!
迈克尔, 你从未告诉我你认得强尼·方廷
Michael, you never told me you knew Johnny Fontane.
-确实, 你想见他吗?  -嗯? 哦, 当然了
-Sure. You wanna meet him? -Huh? Oh, well, sure.
-我父亲帮助他建立他的事业  -是吗?
-My father helped him with his career. -He did?
怎么做的?
How?
我只有一颗心
♪ I have but one heart
-我们先听这首唱  -不, 迈克尔
-Let's listen to the song. -No Michael.
与你分享
♪ To share with you
我只有一颗心
♪ I have but one heart
与你分享
♪ To share with you
我只有一个梦想
♪ I have but one dream
可以坚持
♪ That I can cling to
你是唯一的梦想
♪ You are the one dream
我祈祷梦想成真
♪ I pray comes true
求你了, 迈克尔, 告诉我
Please, Michael. Tell me.
强尼刚出道时
When Johnny was first starting out
跟一个大乐队的领班签了个人服务合同
he was signed to this personal
service contract with a big bandleader.
随着他的职业生涯越来越好, 他想从中解脱出来
And as his career got better and better,
he wanted to get out of it.
强尼是我父亲的教子
Now, Johnny is my father's godson
于是我父亲去见了乐队领班
and my father went to see this bandleader
而且出10000元要他与强尼解约
and he offered him $ 10,000 to let Johnny go.
但乐队领班说不行
But the bandleader said no.
第二天我父亲再去见他, 只是这次是带着卢卡·布拉西去的
So the next day my father went to see him,
only this time with Luca Brasi.
不到1个小时
And within an hour
他签了解约书, 只收了1000元的支票
he signed a release for a certified check of $1,000.
他是怎么办到的?
How'd he do that?
我父亲给了他一个他无法拒绝的提议
My father made him an offer he couldn't refuse.
什么提议?
What was that?
卢卡·布拉西用枪顶着他的头
Luca Brasi held a gun to his head
我父亲向他保证, 合同上要么是他的脑子, 要么是他的签名
and my father assured him that either his brains
or his signature would be on the contract.
这是真实的故事
That's a true story.
凯, 那是我的家庭, 不是我
That's my family, Kay. It's not me.
我会处理的
I'll take care of it.
我要你找到桑蒂诺, 叫他到办公室来
I want you to find Santino. Tell him to come to the office.
你好吗, 弗雷多?
How are you, Fredo?
弗雷多, 我哥哥弗雷多. 这是凯·亚当斯
Fredo, my brother Fredo. This is Kay Adams.
-嗨 -你好吗?
-Hi. -How ya doin'?
-这是我弟弟迈克 -玩的开心吗?
-This is my brother Mike. -Are you having a good time?
是的. 这是你的朋友, 唔?
Yeah. This is your friend, huh?
我不知道该怎么办
I don't know what to do.
我的嗓子很虚弱, 很虚弱
My voice is weak. It's weak.
不管怎样, 如果我能出演这个角色
Anyway, if I had this part in the picture, you know
我会再次走红的
it puts me right back up on top again.
但是... 这个人在那里, 他不会给我, 工作室的负责人
But this... This man out there,
he won't give it to me, the head of the studio.
-他叫什么名字?  -沃尔茨. 沃尔茨, 他...
-What's his name? -Woltz. Woltz, he...
他不肯给我, 他说没有机会, 没有机会
He won't give it to me, and he says there's no chance, no chance.
桑尼?
Sonny?
桑尼, 你在里面吗?
Sonny, you in there?
什么事?
What?
老头子要见你
The old man wants to see you.
好, 马上去
Yeah, one minute.
哦, 桑尼!
Oh, Sonny!
一个月前
A month ago
他买下这本畅销书的电影版权
he bought the movie rights to this book. A best-seller.
主角是一个像我一样的人
And the main character is a guy just like me.
为什么, 我甚至不需要演戏, 做我自己就好
Why, I wouldn't even have to act. Just be myself.
哦, 教父, 我不知该怎么办
Oh, Godfather, I don't know what to do.
你要表现得像个男人!
You can act like a man!
你是怎么回事?
What's the matter with you?
你变成这样了吗?
Is this how you turned out?
一个像女人一样哭泣的好莱坞同性恋?
A Hollywood finocchio that cries like a woman?
"我该怎么办? 我该怎么办?"
"What can I do? What can I do?"
这是什么废话?
What is that nonsense?
愚蠢!
Ridiculous!
-你花时间陪伴家人了吗?  -我当然有
-You spend time with your family? -Sure I do.
很好
Good.
不花时间和家人在一起的男人, 永远不是真正的男人
Because the man who doesn't spend time
with his family can never be a real man.
过来
Come here.
你看来糟透了, 我要你多吃点
You look terrible. I want you to eat.
我要你好好休息
I want you to rest well
一个月后, 这位好莱坞大佬会给你想要的
and a month from now this Hollywood
big shot's gonna give you what you want.
太晚了, 他们一周后就开拍
Too late. They start shooting in a week.
我会给他一个他无法拒绝的提议
I'm gonna make him an offer he can't refuse.
现在出去玩吧, 好好享受, 忘掉这些废话
Now just go outside, enjoy yourself,
and forget about all this nonsense.
听着, 我想让你把这一切都交给我
Listen. I want you to leave it all to me.
好吧
All right.
我女儿和新郎什么时候离开?
What time does my daughter leave with the bridegroom?
他们切完蛋糕后, 几分钟
In a few minutes, right after they cut the cake.
你的新女婿, 我们要给他重要职务吗?
Now, your new son-in-law, we give him something important?
永远不要
Never.
给他一份生计, 但不要和他讨论家族生意
Give him a living but never discuss the family business with him.
还有什么事?
What else?
维吉尔·索洛佐来过电话
Virgil Sollozzo called.
我们必须在下周安排跟他见面
We have to give him a day sometime next week.
等你从加州回来我们再讨论他
We'll discuss him when you come back from California.
我什么时候要去加利福尼亚了?
When am I going to California?
我想让你今晚就去
I want you to go tonight.
我要你和这个
I want you to talk to
电影大亨谈谈, 把强尼的事摆平
this movie big shot and settle this business for Johnny.
如果没有别的事, 我想去参加我女儿的婚礼了
If there's nothing else, I'd like to go to my daughter's wedding.
卡洛, 我们要拍照了
Carlo, we're gonna take the picture.
等一下
Wait a minute.
不, 迈克尔, 我不行
No, Michael, not me.
再靠近一点. 好了, 就这样. 就像现在这样, 别动
Just a little closer. Okay, that's it. Just like that now. Hold it.
(沃尔茨国际影业)
好了, 开始说吧
All right, start talking.
嗯哼, 我是强尼·方廷的朋友派来的
Uh-huh. I was sent by a friend of Johnny Fontane.
这位朋友是我的委托人, 如果沃尔兹先生能帮我们一个小忙
This friend is my client. He and would give his undying friendship
他愿意把他永恒的友谊献给沃尔兹先生
to Mr. Woltz, if Mr. Woltz would grant us a small favor.
继续说下去
Woltz is listening.
让强尼出演你下周要开始的那部新战争片
Give Johnny the part in that new war film you're starting next week.
嗯... 你的朋友会帮沃尔兹先生什么忙?
And uh... what favor would your friend grant Mr. Woltz?
你会遇到一些工会问题, 我的委托人可以让他们消失
You're gonna have some union problems,
My client could make them disappear.
此外, 你的一位抽大麻的顶级明星
Also, one of your top stars has just moved
现在吸起海洛因了
from marijuana to heroin.
你想胁迫我吗?
Are you trying to muscle me?
绝对不是
Absolutely not.
听着, 你这个油腔滑调狗娘养的!
Listen to me, you smooth-talking son of a bitch!
让我对你及你的老板说清楚, 不管他是谁
Let me lay it on the line for you and your boss, whoever he is!
强尼·方廷永远得不到那个角色
Johnny Fontane will never get that movie.
我不在乎有多少意大利佬, 几内亚佬, 意大利佬突然冒出来
I don't care how many dago, guinea,
wop greaseball goombahs come outta the woodwork.
我是德裔爱尔兰人
I'm German-Irish.
好吧, 让我告诉你, 我的德国朋友
Well, let me tell you something, my kraut mick friend.
我会给你制造很多麻烦, 你都不知道是什么打击了你
I'll make so much trouble for you, you won't know what hit you.
沃尔兹先生, 我是一名律师, 我没有威胁过...
Mr. Woltz. I'm a lawyer. I have not threatened...
我认识纽约几乎所有的大律师, 你到底是谁?
I know almost every big lawyer in New York. Who the hell are you?
我有一个特殊的做法, 我只有一个委托人
I have a special practice. I handle one client.
你有我的电话号码了, 我等你的电话
Now you have my number. I'll wait for your call.
顺便说一下, 我很喜欢你的电影
By the way, I admire your pictures very much.
摸清他的底细
Check him out.
真是美极了
This is really beautiful.
看看这个, 原本是用来装饰王宫的
Look at this. Used to decorate the palace of a king.
哦, 是的, 很漂亮
Oh, yeah. Very nice.
你为什么不说你为柯里昂工作, 汤姆?
Why didn't you say you worked for Corleone, Tom?
我以为你只是个廉价的二流骗子
I thought you were just some cheap, two-bit hustler
是强尼派来吓唬我的
Johnny was running in, trying to bluff me.
除非真的有必要, 否则我不想提起他的名字
I don't like to use his name unless it's really necessary.
-汤姆, 你喝得怎么样?  -很好
-How's your drink, Tom? -Fine.
跟我到这边来, 我想让你看看真正漂亮的东西
Hey come on over here with me.
I want to show you something really beautiful.
你很欣赏美, 对吧, 汤姆?
You do appreciate beauty, don't you, Tom?
这里, 这匹马价值60万元
There you are. $600,000 on four hooves.
我敢打赌, 俄国沙皇也从来没有为一匹马花过这么多钱
I'll bet Russian czars never paid that kind of dough for a single horse.
喀土穆, 喀土穆
Khartoum. Khartoum.
不过我不会用他来比赛, 我要把他当种马
I'm not gonna race him, though. I'm gonna put him out to stud.
-谢谢, 托尼 -不客气
-Thanks, Tony. -You're welcome.
-来吧  -我们去吃点东西, 唔?
-Come on. -Let's get something to eat, huh?
柯里昂先生是强尼的教父
Mr. Corleone is Johnny's godfather.
对意大利人来说, 这是一种宗教上的, 神圣的, 亲密关系
To the Italian people, that's a very religious, sacred, close relationship.
我尊重这一点
I respect that.
告诉他, 他可以问我其它问题
Just tell him he should ask me anything else.
这件事我不能帮忙
But this is one favor I can't give him.
第一次被拒绝后, 他从不要求第二次帮忙. 理解吗?
He never asks a second favor when he's been refused the first. Understood?
你不了解, 强尼·方廷永远别想演那部电影
You don't understand. Johnny Fontane never gets that movie.
那个角色对他来说很完美
That part is perfect for him.
会让他成为巨星
It'll make him a big star.
我要把他赶出这个行业
I'm gonna run him out of the business.
让我告诉你为什么
Let me tell you why.
强尼·方廷毁了沃尔茨国际公司 最有价值的一个女星
Johnny Fontane ruined one of Woltz International's most valuable proteges.
5年来, 我们不断地训练她
For five years, we had her under training.
歌唱课, 表演课, 舞蹈课
Singing lessons, acting lessons, dancing lessons.
我在她身上花了几十万美元
I spent hundreds of thousands of dollars on her.
我要让她成为一个巨星
I was gonna make her a big star.
让我更坦率地说
And let me be even more frank.
我只是想告诉你, 我不是一个铁石心肠的人, 也不全是金钱
Just to show you that I'm not a hard-hearted man.
that it's not all dollars and cents.
她很漂亮, 她那么年轻, 那么天真!
She was beautiful. She was young, she was innocent!
她是我见过的最漂亮的, 我拥有她就等于拥有全世界!
She was the greatest piece of ass I've ever had
and I've had 'em all over the world!
然后强尼·方廷出现了
And then Johnny Fontane comes along
带着磁性的嗓音和意大利的魅力
with his olive oil voice and guinea charm.
她跑掉了
And she runs off.
她抛弃了这一切, 只是为了让我看起来很可笑!
She threw it all away just to make me look ridiculous!
像我这种地位的人不能让自己看起来很可笑!
And a man in my position can't afford to be made to look ridiculous!
现在你给我滚出去!
Now you get the hell outta here!
如果那个混蛋想对我动粗
And if that goombah tries any rough stuff
你告诉他我不是乐队领班
you tell him I ain't no bandleader.
是的, 我听过那个故事了
Yeah. I heard that story.
谢谢你的晚餐, 让我度过了一个愉快的夜晚
Thank you for the dinner and a very pleasant evening.
也许你能派车送我去机场
Maybe your car could take me to the airport.
柯里昂先生是一个坚持要立即听到坏消息的人
Mr. Corleone is a man who insists on hearing bad news immediately.
-汤姆, 你不会太累吧?  -不累, 我在飞机上睡过了
-You're not too tired, Tom? -No, I slept on the plane.
我这里有索洛佐的资料
I have the Sollozzo notes here.
现在…
Now...
索洛佐被称为"土耳其人"
Sollozzo is known as"The Turk."
他应该很擅长用刀
He's supposed to be very good with a knife
但只有在生意上有合理的抱怨时才会用
but only in matters of business with some sort of reasonable complaint.
唔, 他是做毒品生意的
Uh, his business is narcotics.
他在土耳其有田地, 那里种着罂粟
He has fields in Turkey, where they grow the poppy.
在西西里, 他有工厂可以把毒品加工成海洛因
And in Sicily he has the plants to process them into heroin.
现在, 他需要现金
Now, he needs cash
还需要警方的保护, 而他也要从中分一杯羹
and he needs protection from the police
for which he gives a piece of the action.
我无法查出保护费是多少
I couldn't find out how much.
在纽约是塔塔基利亚家族在保护他
The Tattaglia family is behind him here in New York.
他们一定也想分占利益
Now, they have to be in it for something.
桑蒂诺·柯里昂
Santino Corleone.
他的犯罪前科呢?
What about his prison record?
有两次, 一次在意大利, 一次在这儿
Two terms, one in Italy, one here.
他是众所周知的大毒枭
He's known as a top narcotics man.
桑蒂诺, 你的想法呢?
Santino, what do you think?
白粉可以赚大钱
There's a lot of money in that white powder.
-汤姆?  -我赞成
-Tom?  -I say, yes.
毒品交易比我们正在研究的任何生意都更有赚钱潜力
There's more money potential in narcotics
than anything else we're looking at.
就算我们不介入, 别人也会介入
If we don't get into it, somebody else will.
也许是五大家族之一, 也许是全部介入
Maybe one of the five families, maybe all of them.
他们会用毒品赚到的钱, 买通警方和政客
With the money they earn, they can buy more police and political power.
到时就会赶上我们
Then they come after us.
现在我们掌握了工会, 掌握了赌场
Now we have the unions, we have the gambling
这些都是最好的东西, 但毒品是未来的东西
and they're the best things to have, but narcotics is a thing of the future.
我们若不能从中分一杯羹
If we don't get a piece of that action
我们就会冒着失去一切的风险
we risk everything we have.
我不是指现在而是10年之后
Not now, but ten years from now.
怎么样? 你的答案是什么, 爸爸?
So? What's your answer gonna be, Pop?
是这样, 柯里昂阁下
There. Don Corleone
我需要一个有势力的朋友
I need a man who has powerful friends.
我需要100万元的现金
I need a million dollars in cash.
柯里昂阁下, 我需要那些你口袋里揣着的政客, 就像有许多硬币一样
I need, Don Corleone, those politicians that you carry
in your pocket, like so many nickels and dimes.
-对我家族有什么利益? -30%回报
-What is the interest for my family? -Thirty percent.
第一年, 你就可进帐3、400万元
In the first year, your end should be 3, 4 million dollars.
然后还会增加
And then it would go up.
塔塔基利亚家族会得到什么好处?
And what is the interest for the Tattaglia family?
我的敬意
My compliments.
我会从我的份额中照顾塔塔基利亚人
I'll take care of the Tattaglias outta my share.
我提供财务、政治和法律的保护, 可以分到30%
So, I receive 30% for finance, political influence and legal protection.
没错
That's right.
你为什么来找我?
Why do you come to me?
为什么我值得你如此慷慨?
Why do I deserve this generosity?
若你能考虑投资100万元现金
If you consider a million dollars in cash just "finance"
我会向你敬礼, 柯里昂阁下
te salud, Don Corleone.
我说我要见你, 是因为我听说你是个正直的人
I said that I would see you because
I heard that you were a serious man
应该受到尊重
to be treated with respect.
但是... 我必须拒绝你
But... I must say no to you.
我会给你我的理由
And I'll give you my reason.
没错, 我是有很多政界的朋友
It's true, I have a lot of friends in politics.
但若他们知道我在搞毒品生意而不再是赌博时
But they wouldn't be friendly very long
他们就不再是我的朋友了
if they knew my business was drugs instead of gambling
他们认为赌博是一种无害的恶习
which they regard as a harmless vice.
但毒品是一门肮脏的生意
But drugs is a dirty business.
-不, 柯里昂阁下... -一个人以什么为生
-No, Don Corleone... -It doesn't make any difference to me
对我来说没有什么区别, 你明白的
what a man does for a living, you understand.
但你的生意...
But your business is...
有一点危险
a little dangerous.
如果你担心你那100万的安全
If you're worried about security for your million
塔塔基利亚家族可以担保
the Tattaglias will guarantee it.
你是说塔塔基利亚家族保证我们的投资...
You're tellin' me the Tattaglias guarantee our investment...
等一下
Wait a minute.
我对我的孩子有感情上的弱点, 我把他们宠坏了, 你也看到了
I have a sentimental weakness for my children...
and I spoil them, as you can see.
他们在该听的时候却在说
They talk when they should listen.
不管怎样, 索洛佐先生
But anyway Signor Sollozzo
我的决定还是不行
my "no" is final.
我要祝贺你的新生意
And I wish to congratulate you on your new business.
我知道你会做得很好, 祝你好运
I know you'll do very well, and good luck to you
尤其是因为你的利益与我的利益并不冲突
especially since your interests don't conflict with mine.
谢谢
Thank you.
桑蒂诺
Santino
过来!
Come here!
你是怎么回事?
What's the matter with you?
我看你和女孩子胡搞之后, 脑子退化了
I think your brain is going soft from all that
comedy you're playing with that young girl.
别让家里以外的人知道你在想什么
Never tell anybody outside the family what you're thinking again.
走吧
Go on.
汤姆, 这是什么乱七八糟的?
Tom, what... What is this nonsense?
这是强尼送来的, 他正在主演那部新电影
It's from Johnny. He's starring in that new film.
好吧, 把它拿走
Well, take it away.
放到那边去
Take it over there.
还有...
And...
叫卢卡·布拉西到这来
tell Luca Brasi to come in.
我有点担心索洛佐这个家伙
I'm a little worried about this Sollozzo fellow.
我要你弄清楚他在耍什么把戏
I want you to find out what he's got under his fingernails.
到塔塔基利亚那边去
Go to the Tattaglias
让他们以为你与我们家族不融洽
and make them think that you're not too happy with our family
尽你所能去查明真相
and find out what you can.
我给你妈妈和桑尼买了一些东西
I got something for your mother and for Sonny
给弗雷多买了一条领带, 给汤姆·哈根买了雷诺兹笔
and a tie for Freddy, and Tom Hagen got the Reynolds pen.
-圣诞节你想要什么?  -我吗? 哦, 只要你
-What do you want for Christmas? -Me? Oh, just you.
来吧, 弗雷多
Andiamo, Fredo.
叫保利备车, 我们要走了
Tell Paulie to get the car. We're going.
好的, 爸
Okay, Pa.
-我来开车, 保利今天早上打电话请了病假  -嗯?
I'll have to get it myself. Paulie called in sick this morning. -Huh?
保利是个好孩子, 我不介意自己开车
Paulie's a good kid. I don't mind gettin' the car.
-圣诞快乐, 卡洛  -谢谢
-Buon natale, Caro. -Gràzie.
-卢卡, 我是布鲁诺·塔塔基利亚  -我知道
-Luca, I am Bruno Tattaglia. -I know.
你喜欢苏格兰威士忌吗?
Do you what Scotch?
战前的
Prewar.
我不喝酒
I don't drink.
你知道我是谁吗?
You know who I am?
我认识你
你和塔塔基利亚家族谈过了, 对吧?
我认为我们可以一起做些生意
我需要像你这么壮的人
我听说你与柯里昂家族不和
想加入我们吗?
我能得到什么好处?
起薪5万元
还不坏
同意了?
汤姆! 汤姆·哈根, 圣诞快乐
Tom! Tom Hagen. Merry Christmas.
我很高兴遇见你
I'm glad I run into you.
-我想跟你聊聊  -我没有时间
-I wanna talk to you. -I haven't got time.
哦, 为我们拨点时间, 军师, 上车吧
Oh, make time, consigliere. Get in the car.
你担心什么?
What are you worried about?
我要杀你的话, 你早就死了
If I wanted to kill you, you'd be dead already.
上车
Get in.
弗雷多, 我买点水果
Fredo, I'm gonna buy some fruit.
好的, 爸
Okay, Pa.
嗨, 圣诞快乐, 我要买些水果
Hi. Merry Christmas. I want some fruit over there.
来3个, 不, 那个给我
Gimme three of them. No, that one.
弗雷多!
Fredo!
爸爸!
Papa!
迈克, 如果我是修女你会更喜欢我吗?
Mike, Would you like me better if I were a nun?
就像小说里的一样, 你知道吗?
Like in the story, you know?
不会
No.
如果我是英格丽·褒曼你会更喜欢我吗?
Well then would you like me better if I were Ingrid Bergman?
这个想法不错
Now that's a thought.
迈克尔
Michael.
不, 如果你是英格丽褒曼我不会更喜欢你
No, I would not like you better if you were Ingrid Bergman.
-迈克... -怎么了?
-Mike... -What's the matter?
[ 维托·柯里昂恐被谋杀 ]
上面没说他是死是活
They don't say if he's dead or alive.
-桑尼, 我是迈克尔  -迈克尔, 你到哪去了?
-Sonny, Michael. -Michael, where you been?
-他没事吧?  -我们还不知道, 有各种各样的说法
-Is he all right? -We don't know yet. There's all kinds of stories.
他伤的很重, 迈克
He was hit bad, Mikey.
-你还在吗? -是的, 我在
-Are you there? -Yeah, I'm here.
-你到哪去了? 我很担心  -汤姆没说我打过电话吗?
-Where you been? I was worried. -Didn't Tom tell you I called?
没有, 听我说, 回家来, 弟弟, 你应该陪妈妈, 听到了吗?
No. Look, come home, kid. You should be with Mama, you hear?
好的
All right.
哦, 我的天啊
Oh, my God.
桑尼
Sonny.
待在后面, 去
Stay back there. Go.
-谁  -开门, 我是克莱门扎
-Who is it? -Open up. It's Clemenza.
又有你老头的消息了
There's more news about your old man.
街头谣传他已经死了
Word is out on the street he's already dead.
-你怎么... 你怎么回事?  -桑尼, 放松点! 放松点!
-What's the matter... What's the matter with you?
-Sonny, take it easy! Take it easy!
保利在哪?
Where was Paulie?
保利病了, 他整个冬天都在生病
Paulie was out sick. He's been sick all winter.
-他病了几次?  -大概3, 4次
-How many times he been sick?
-Only maybe three, four times.
我问弗雷要不要换一个保镖, 他说不用
I asked Freddy if he wants a different bodyguard. He said no.
帮我个忙, 现在就去接他, 我不管他病得有多重
Do me a favour, pick him up right now. I don't care how sick he is.
只要他还在呼吸, 我要你现在就把他带到我父亲的房子去
If he's breathin', I want you to bring him to my father's house now.
你明白吗? 现在!
You understand? Now!
好, 你想让我派人到这边来吗?
Yeah, You want me to send people here?
不用, 只需你和他, 去吧
No, no, no. Just you and him. Go ahead.
好吧, 我已经派了几个人来了
All right. I'm havin' a couple of our people come to the house.
-你好?  -桑蒂诺·柯里昂吗?
-Hello? -Santino Corleone?
-我是 -汤姆·哈根在我们手上
-Yeah. -We have Tom hagen.
大约3小时后, 我们会释放他
In about three hours,
he'll be released with our proposition.
在你做任何事之前, 先听听他说的话
Listen to everything he has to say before you do anything.
木己成舟
What's done is done.
别发你那出名的脾气, 好吗, 桑尼?
And don't lose that famous temper of yours, huh, Sonny?
不会的, 我会等
No, I'll wait.
你的老板死了
Your boss is dead.
我知道你不是这个家族喜欢动武的一员
I know you're not in the muscle end of the family, Tom
所以我不想让你害怕
so I don't want you to be scared.
我希望你能帮助柯里昂一家, 我希望你也能帮助我
I want you to help the Corleones and I want you to help me.
接了你大约1小时后
Yeah, we got him outside his office
我们己在他的办公室外干掉他了
about an hour after we picked you up.
喝吧
Drink it.
现在全看你的了, 让我与桑尼和平解决一切
So now, it's up to you to make the peace between me and Sonny.
桑尼对我的交易很热衷, 不是吗?
Sonny was hot for my deal, wasn't he?
而且你知道这是正确的做法
And you knew it was the right thing to do.
桑尼会不惜一切追杀你的
Sonny will come after you with everything he's got.
这肯定是他的第一反应
That'll be his first reaction, sure.
所以你必须得跟他讲点道理
That's why you gotta talk some sense into him.
塔塔基利亚家族和他们所有的人都支持我
The Tattaglia family is behind me with all their people.
纽约其它的家族
The other New York families
将支持任何能阻止全面战争的措施
will go along with anything that will prevent a full-scale war.
让我们面对现实吧, 汤姆
Let's face it, Tom
我们全都尊敬他
and all due respect
但教父己今非昔比, 愿他安息
the Don, rest in peace, was slippin'.
10年前我能对付他吗?
Ten years ago, could I have gotten to him?
现在他已经死了
Well, now he's dead.
他死了, 汤姆
He's dead, Tom
没有什么能让他复生
and nothing can bring him back.
所以你得和桑尼谈谈
So you gotta talk to Sonny.
也得说服两个大头目, 那个泰西欧, 那个肥仔克莱门扎
You gotta talk to the caporegimes, that Tessio, that fat Clemenza.
那是笔好生意, 汤姆
It's good business, Tom.
我试试看
I'll try.
不过即使是桑尼也阻止不了卢卡·布拉西
But even Sonny won't be able to call off Luca Brasi.
是啊, 呃... 这个卢卡让我来担心
Yeah. Well... Let me worry about Luca.
你只管说服桑尼
You just talk to Sonny.
以及他另外两个兄弟
And the other two kids.
-我尽力而为  -很好
-I'll do my best. -Good.
现在, 你可以走了
Now, you can go.
我不喜欢暴力, 汤姆, 我是个生意人
I don't like violence, Tom. I'm a businessman.
流血的代价太高了
Blood is a big expense.
他还活着
He's still alive.
他们打了他5枪, 他还活着!
They hit him with five shots, and he's still alive!
这对我来说是坏运气
That's bad luck for me
如果如果你做不成这笔交易, 你也会倒霉
and bad luck for you if you don't make that deal.
迈克尔
Michael.
你妈妈在医院陪着你爸爸
Your mother's over in the hospital with your father.
看起来他会挺过来的, 感谢上帝
Looks like he's gonna pull through, thank God.
-这是血海深仇  -你觉得呢?
-索洛佐, 菲利普·塔塔格里亚, 布鲁诺·塔塔格利亚, 拉蒙...
-That's a lot of bad blood. -What do you think?
-Sollozzo, Philip Tattaglia, Bruno Tattaglia, Ramon...
太过分了, 我觉得这不是冲着你来的
It's too far. I think it's too personal.
-你要把那些家伙都杀了吗?  -嘿, 迈克, 帮我个忙, 别插手
-You gonna kill all those guys? -Hey, stay out of it, Mickey. Do me a favour.
索洛佐是关键, 除掉他一切就好办了
Sollozzo's the key. You get rid of him, everything falls into line.
卢卡呢? 索洛佐似乎并不担心卢卡
What about Luca? Sollozzo didn't seem worried about Luca.
我不知道
I don't know.
如果卢卡出卖了我们, 我们就麻烦大了
If Luca sold out, we're in a lot of trouble.
有人能联系上卢卡吗?
Has anyone been able to get in touch with Luca?
我们试了一整夜, 他可能住在别处了
We've been tryin' all night. He might be shacked up.
迈克, 帮我个忙, 再打电话给卢卡
Hey, Mickey, do me a favor, try him again.
卢卡从不在外留宿, 他办完事总会立刻回家
Luca never sleeps over with a broad.
He always goes home when he's through.
汤姆, 你是军师
Well, Tom, you're consigliere.
上帝保佑, 要是老头死了, 我们该怎么办?
What do we do if the old man dies, God forbid?
万一我们失去了老头
If we lose the old man
我们就失去了政治人脉, 失去了一半的力量
we lose our political contacts and half our strength.
纽约其它的家族为了避免长期的毁灭性战争
The other New York families might wind up supporting Sollozzo
可能会联合支持索洛佐
just to avoid a long destructive war.
现在差不多是1946年了
This is almost 1946.
没有人想再流血了
Nobody wants bloodshed anymore.
如果你父亲死了
If your father dies
就由你来做决定了, 桑尼
you'll make the deal, Sonny.
你说得倒轻巧, 那不是你父亲
That's easy for you to say. He's not your father.
我对他来说就像你或迈克一样, 都是儿子
I was as much a son to him as you or Mike.
什么事?
What is it?
嘿, 保利, 我叫你在外面守着
Hey, Paulie, I thought I told you to stay put.
大门口的人, 他们说收到了一包东西
The guy at the gates, they say they got a package.
是吗? 泰西欧, 去看看是怎么回事
Yeah? Tessio, go see what it is.
你想让我留在这儿吗?
You want me to hang around?
-是的, 留在这儿吧  -你还好吧?
-Yeah, hang around.-You all right?
我很好
I'm fine.
是吗? 冰箱里有一些食物, 你饿了吗?
Yeah? There's some food in the icebox. You hungry?
不, 没关系, 谢谢
No, it's all right. Thanks.
来点儿白兰地怎么样? 出汗是件好事
How 'bout a little brandy? That's good to sweat it out.
-是的 -去吧, 孩子
-Sure. -Go ahead, son.
这也许是个好主意
That might be a good idea.
我要你马上解决掉那个王八蛋
I want you to take care of that son of a bitch right away.
保利出卖了老头
Paulie sold out the old man.
我不想再见到他
I don't wanna see him again.
这是你清单上的第一件事, 明白吗?
Make that first thing on your list. Understand?
明白
Understood.
嘿, 迈克, 明天你带几个人
Hey, Mickey, tomorrow you get a couple of guys.
到卢卡的公寓去看看, 等他出现
Go to Luca's apartment. Wait for him to show up.
也许我们不该直接把迈克牵扯进来
Maybe we shouldn't get Mike mixed up in this too directly.
听我说, 待在家里接电话, 那会有大帮助的
Listen, hang around the house on the phone. It'll be a big help.
再试试打给卢卡, 打吧
Try Luca again. Go ahead.
-这是什么鬼东西?  -这是西西里人的口信
-What the hell is this? -It's a Sicilian message.
意思是卢卡·布拉西与鱼同眠了
It means Luca Brasi sleeps with the fishes.
-我要走了 -你什么时候回家?
-I'm goin' now. -What time you gonna be home?
我不知道, 也许会很晚
I don't know. Probably late.
-别忘了煎饼卷 -好, 好, 好
-Don't forget the cannoli. -Yeah, yeah, yeah.
洛可, 坐另一边去
Rocco, sit on the other side.
你挡住后视镜了
You block the rearview mirror.
桑尼疯了
That Sonny's running wild.
他已经在想去睡床垫, 跟对手开战了
He's thinkin' of goin' to the mattresses already.
我们得在西区找个地方藏身
We gotta find a spot over on the West Side.
我们去西43街309号试试
We'll try 309 West 43rd Street.
-你知道西区有什么好地方吗?  -嗯, 我想想看
-You know any good spots on the West Side?
-Yeah, I'll think about it.
一边开车一边想吧
Think while you're drivin'.
这个月我要找个时候去一趟纽约
I wanna hit New York sometime this month.
倒车出去时留意小孩子
And watch out for the kids when you're backin' out.
保利, 我要你沿着39街走, 去卡洛·桑托斯
Paulie, I want you to go down 39th Street, Carlo Santos
去买18张床垫给他们睡
pick up 18 mattresses for the guys to sleep.
然后把账单拿给我
Bring me the bill.
-好的, 没问题  -确保要干净的
-Yeah, all right. -Make sure they're clean.
那些家伙会被困在里面很长一段时间
Those guys are gonna be stuck up in there for a long time.
它们很干净, 他们告诉我会消灭蛀虫的
They're clean. They told me they exterminate them.
"消灭"? 这个词用的不好
"Exterminate"? That's a bad word to use.
消灭, 捉住这个家伙
Exterminate. Get this guy.
小心点, 这样我们就不会消灭你了!
Watch out, so we don't exterminate you!
-你觉得好笑吗?  -我要尿尿
-Youse funny, or what? - I gotta take a leak.
嘿, 保利? 靠边停车, 好吗?
Hey, Paulie? Pull over, will you?
把枪留下
Leave the gun.
把煎饼卷给我
Take the cannoli.
嘿, 迈克! 嘿, 迈克!
Hey, Mike! Hey, Mikey!
哎
Yeah.
有你的电话
You're wanted on the telephone.
-是谁?  -是个女孩子
-Who is it? -It's some girl.
-你好, 凯?  -你爸爸怎么样?
-Hello, Kay? -How's your father?
他很好, 他能活过来
He's good. He's gonna make it.
我爱你
I love you.
-嗯?  -我爱你
-Huh? -I love you.
-迈克尔?  -是, 我知道
-Michael? -Yeah, I know.
告诉我你爱我
Tell me you love me.
我不能说
I can't talk.
你不能说吗?
Can't you say it?
是, 我们晚上见
Yeah, I'll see you tonight.
迈克, 你为什么不告诉那个漂亮女孩你爱她?
Hey Mikey, why don't you tell that nice girl you love her?
我全心全意的爱你
I love you with all my heart!
如果我不能很快再见到你, 我会死的!
If I don't see you again a-soon, I'm-a gonna die!
到这来, 年轻人, 学点东西
Come over here, kid. Learn somethin'.
也许有一天你得为20个男人做饭
You might have to cook for 20 guys someday.
你看到了吗? 先放一点油, 然后炒一些大蒜
You see? You start out with a little bit of oil. Then you fry some garlic.
然后你加入一些西红柿, 一些番茄酱
Then you throw in some tomatoes, some tomato paste.
煎一下, 你要确保它不会黏锅底
You fry it. You make sure it doesn't stick.
煮开了之后, 把香肠和肉丸都放进去
When you got it to a boil, shove in all your sausage and meatballs.
嗯?
Huh?
再加一点点酒
And a little bit of wine.
以及一点点糖
And a little bit of sugar.
这是我的秘方
And that's my trick.
你能不能别废话了?
Why don't you cut the crap?
我有更重要的事让你去做
I got more important things for you to do.
保利呢?
How's Paulie?
哦, 保利, 你再也见不到他了
Oh, Paulie. Won't see him no more.
你要去哪?
Where you going?
到城里去
To the city.
派几个保镖跟他一起去, 好吗?
Send some bodyguards with him, all right?
我只是去医院看爸爸
I'm just going to the hospital see Pop.
我不管, 派人跟他一起去
Nevermind, send somebody with him.
他不会有事的, 索洛佐知道他是平民
He'll be all right. Sollozzo knows he's a civilian.
-好吧, 小心点, 嗯?  -是的, 先生
-All right. Be careful, huh? -Yes, sir.
不管怎样都要派人跟他一起去
Send somebody with him anyway.
-我得走了  -我能与你一起去吗?
I have to go. Can I go with you?
不, 凯, 那儿会有警探, 还有来自媒体的人
No, Kay. There's gonna be detectives there. People from the press.
那我在出租车里等你
I'll ride in a cab.
我不想让你卷入这件事
I don't want you to get involved.
我什么时候能再见到你?
When will I see you again?
回新罕布什尔去
Go back to New Hampshire
我会打电话到你父母家找你
and I'll call you at your parents' house.
我什么时候能再见到你, 迈克尔?
When will I see you again, Michael?
我不知道
I don't know.
你在这儿干什么?
What are you doing here?
现在不是探病时间
You're not supposed to be here now.
我是迈克尔·柯里昂
I'm Michael Corleone.
这是我爸爸
This is my father.
这里没有人, 守卫到哪儿去了?
There's nobody here. What happened to the guards?
你父亲来访的人太多了, 他们干扰了医院的服务
Your father just had too many visitors.
They interfered with hospital service.
警察在10分钟前让他们离开了
The police made them leave about ten minutes ago.
请帮我接长滩45620
Get me Long Beach 4-5-6-2-0, please.
护士, 等一下, 先别走
Nurse, wait a minute. Stay here.
桑尼, 我是迈克尔, 我在医院
Sonny, Michael. I'm at the hospital.
-听着, 我很晚才到这儿, 这儿没有人  -什么? 没有人?
Listen. I got here late. There's nobody here.
-What? Nobody?
没有人, 泰西欧的人不在, 也没有警探, 没有人
Nobody. No Tessio's men, no detectives, nobody.
爸爸单独一个人在这儿
Pop is all alone.
-别慌, 我马上派人去  -我不会慌
-Don't panic. We'll send somebody. -I won't panic.
我很抱歉, 但你必须离开
I'm sorry, but you will have to leave.
嗯...
Uh...
你帮我把我父亲转移到另一个房间
You and I are gonna move my father to another room.
你能把那些管子断开吗? 这样我们就可以把床搬出去了
Can you disconnect those tubes so we can move the bed out?
-那是不可能的  -你认识我父亲吗?
-That's out of the question. -Do you know my father?
有人要来杀他, 你明白吗?
Men are coming here to kill him. You understand?
现在, 请你给我帮忙
Now, help me, please.
你是谁?
Who are you?
我是恩佐... 那个面包师
I am Enzo... the baker.
-你还记得我吧? -恩佐?
-You remember me? -Enzo?
是的, 我是恩佐
Yes, Enzo.
你最好离开这儿, 恩佐, 这里会有麻烦的
You better get out of here, Enzo. There's gonna be trouble.
要是有麻烦, 我留在这儿帮你
If there is trouble, I stay here to help you.
为了你父亲, 为了你父亲
For your father. For your father.
好吧, 听我说
All right, listen.
在外面等我, 到医院门口, 好吧?
Wait for me outside, in front of the hospital. All right?
我马上出来, 快去
I'll be out in a minute. Go ahead.
好的, 好的
Okay. Okay.
躺在这儿吧, 爸爸
Just lie here, Pop.
现在我来照顾你
I'll take care of you now.
现在我陪着你. 我和你在一起
I'm with you now. I'm with you.
把这个扔掉
Get rid of these.
到这儿来
Come here.
把手放在口袋里, 就像你有枪一样
Put your hand in your pocket like you have a gun.
你不会有事的
You'll be all right.
你会没事的
You'll be okay.
你做得很好
You did good.
这是干什么?
我以为我把你们这些混混全关住了
I thought I got all you guinea hoods locked up.
你在这里干什么?
What are you doing here?
守卫我父亲的人发生了什么事, 副巡长?
What happened to the men who were guarding my father, Captain?
干吗, 你这个小混混, 你对我的事指手画脚!
Why, you little punk.
What the hell are you doing telling me my business!
是我把那些人全赶走的, 嗯
I pulled them guys off of here, eh.
你滚出去, 离这家医院远点
You get out of here and stay away from this hospital.
除非你在我父亲的病房周围安排了警卫, 否则我不会走
I'm not moving until you put some guards around my father's room.
菲尔, 把他带走!
Phil, take him in!
那孩子是清白的, 副巡长
The kid's clean, Captain.
他是战争英雄, 从未被当场逮住...
He's a war hero. He's never been busted...
该死的, 我说把他带走
Goddamn it, I said take him in.
那个土耳其人给了你多少钱让你陷害我父亲, 副巡长?
What's the Turk paying you to set up my father, Captain?
抓牢他, 让他站起来, 让他站稳
Take ahold of him. Stand him up. Stand him up straight.
我是柯里昂家族的律师
I'm the attorney for the Corleone family.
这些人是受雇保护维托·柯里昂的私家侦探
These men are private detectives hired to protect Vito Corleone.
他们有携带武器的执照
They're licensed to carry firearms.
如果你干预, 你将不得不在早上出现在法官面前并提出理由
If you interfere, you'll have to appear before a judge
in the morning and show cause.
好吧, 让他走
All right, let him go.
走吧
Come on.
这些新面孔是怎么回事
What's with all the new faces?
我们现在需要他们
Gonna need 'em now.
医院的事情发生后, 桑尼气疯了
After the hospital thing, Sonny got mad.
我们今晨4点干掉了布鲁诺·塔塔基利亚
We hit Bruno Tattaglia at 4:00 this morning.
天呐
Jesus Christ.
这里看起来像个堡垒
Looks like a fortress around here.
Tamaduch! Hey...
街上一天24小时, 都有100个枪手在巡逻
A hundred button men on the street, 24 hours a day.
那个土耳其人露出屁股上的一根毛, 他就死定了, 相信我
That Turk shows one hair on his ass, he's dead. Believe me.
嘿, 迈克尔, 到这里来, 让我看看你
Hey, Michael, come here. Let me look at you.
你看起来很漂亮, 漂亮极了, 非常漂亮
You look beautiful. Just beautiful. You're gorgeous.
嘿, 你们听我说
Hey, listen to this.
那土耳其人, 他想谈判
The Turk, he wants to talk.
想象一下这个狗娘养的有多紧张
Imagine the nerve on this son of a bitch.
昨晚整我们, 今天想和谈
Craps out last night, he wants a meeting today.
-他说什么?  -他说了什么?
-What'd he say? -What did he say?
他想让我们派迈克尔去听这个提议
He wants us to send Michael to hear the proposition.
并保证交易条件好到我们不会拒绝
And the promise is that the deal is so good that we can't refuse.
布鲁诺·塔塔基利亚呢?
What about Bruno Tattaglia?
那是条件的一部分
That's part of the deal.
布鲁诺取消了他们对我父亲所做的一切
Bruno cancels out what they did to my father.
桑尼, 我们应该听听他们要说什么
Sonny, we ought to hear what they have to say.
不, 不, 不再听了, 这次不行, 军师
No. No. No more. Not this time, Consigliere.
不再和谈, 不再讨论, 不再玩索洛佐的把戏
No more meetings, no discussions, no more Sollozzo tricks.
你给他们一个信息, 我要索洛佐
You give them one message. I want Sollozzo.
如果不行, 那就是全面战争, 我们去睡床垫
If not, it's all-out war. We go to the mattresses.
有些家族是不会坐视不管的
Some of the other families won't sit still for a war.
-然后他们把索洛佐交给我  -你父亲不会喜欢这样的
-Then they hand me Sollozzo. -Your father wouldn't like this.
这是生意, 不是私人恩怨
This is business, not personal.
他们射杀了我父亲...
They shot my father...
即使射杀你父亲也是生意
Even shooting your father was business
不是私人恩怨, 桑尼
not personal, Sonny.
那生意就必须要停, 行吗?
Well, then business will have to suffer, all right?
听着, 帮我个忙, 汤姆
And listen, do me a favor, Tom.
别再建议我如何让事情过去
No more advice on how to patch things up.
只要帮我赢, 好吗?
Just help me win, please. All right?
我查出了打断迈克下巴的麦克劳斯基
I found out about this McCluskey who broke Mike's jaw.
他什么情况?
What about him?
他肯定在索洛佐的工资名单中, 而且是一大笔钱
He's definitely on Sollozzo's payroll, and for big money.
麦克劳斯基同意做土耳其人的保镖
McCluskey has agreed to be the Turk's bodyguard.
桑尼, 你必须明白的是
What you have to understand, Sonny
当索洛佐受到这样的保护时
is that while Sollozzo's being guarded like this
没人可以碰他了
he is invulnerable.
从来没有人枪杀过纽约警察巡长, 从来没有
Nobody has ever gunned down a New York police captain. Never.
那将是灾难性的
It would be disastrous.
所有五大家族都会追杀你, 桑尼
All the five families would come after you, Sonny.
柯里昂家族会被孤立
The Corleone family would be outcast.
即使是老头的政治保护都会消失
Even the old man's political protection would run for cover.
所以帮我个忙
So do me a favor.
别轻举妄动
Take this into consideration.
好吧, 我们等
All right, we'll wait.
我们不能等
We can't wait.
不能等
Can't wait.
我不在乎索洛佐怎么说交易的事, 他要杀了爸爸, 就是这样
I don't care what Sollozzo says about a deal.
He's gonna kill Pop. That's it.
这对他来说是关键
That's the key for him.
必须干掉索洛佐
Got to get Sollozzo.
迈克说的对
Mike is right.
我先问你个问题
Let me ask you something first.
这个麦克劳斯基呢, 嗯?
What about this McCluskey, eh?
我们该拿这个条子怎么办?
What do we do with this cop?
他们想和我开个会, 对吧?
They want to have a meeting with me, right?
那会是我, 麦克劳斯基和索洛佐
It will be me, McCluskey and Sollozzo.
我们来约定会议
Let's set the meeting.
让我们的线人去查一下会议的地点
Get our informers to find out where it's going to be held.
我们坚持必须是公开场所, 酒吧或餐厅
We insist it's a public place. A bar, a restaurant.
有人的地方, 这样我才有安全感
Someplace where there's people, so I feel safe.
第一次见到他们时, 他们会搜我的身, 对吧?
They're gonna search me when I first meet them, right?
所以我不能随身携带武器
So I can't have a weapon on me then.
如果克莱门扎能想出一个办法
But if Clemenza can figure a way
预先为我埋下武器
to have a weapon planted there for me
我就能杀了他们俩
then I'll kill them both.
嘿! 你打算怎么做? 乖乖的大学生, 嗯?
Hey! What are you gonna do? Nice college boy, huh?
你不是不想卷入家族生意吗?
Didn't want to get mixed up in the family business.
现在你又想枪杀一个警察巡长?
Now you want to gun down a police captain?
为什么? 因为他在你脸上打了一拳, 嗯?
Why? 'Cause he slapped you in the face a little bit, eh?
你以为这是在军队吗, 在一英里外就开枪?
What do you think this is the army, where you shoot them a mile away?
你必须靠近, 像这样, 砰!
You gotta get up close, like this, bada bing!
你把他们的脑浆都溅到你漂亮的常春藤盟校套装上了
You blow their brains all over your nice Ivy League suit.
-拜托, 迈克, 你把这件事看得太个人化了
-Come on, Mikey... You're taking this very personal.
汤姆, 这是公事, 而他却非常非常个人化了
Tom, this is business, and this man is taking it very, very personal.
谁说不能杀条子了?
Where does it say you can't kill a cop?
-别这样, 迈克  -汤姆, 慢着
-Come on, Mikey. -Tom, wait a minute.
我说的是一个和毒品卷入在一起的条子
I'm talking about a cop that's mixed up in drugs.
我说的是一个不诚实的条子
I'm talking about a dishonest cop
一个被卷入不法勾当而得到应有惩罚的奸诈条子
a crooked cop who got mixed up in the rackets
and got what was coming to him.
这是一个极好的故事
That's a terrific story.
我们的工资单上不是有报社的人吗, 汤姆?
We have newspaper people on the payroll, don't we, Tom?
他们可能喜欢这样的故事
They might like a story like that.
他们可能, 他们只是可能
They might. They just might.
这不是个人化的, 桑尼, 完全是公事
It's not personal, Sonny. It's strictly business.
做过表面处理了
It's as cold as they come.
无法追踪, 所以你不用担心指纹, 迈克
Impossible to trace, so you don't worry about prints, Mike.
我在扳机和枪托上贴了特殊胶布
I put a special tape on the trigger and the butt.
来, 试试看
Here. Try it.
怎么了, 扳机太紧了吗?
What's the matter, the trigger too tight?
-我的耳朵  -我没安装消声器
-My ears. -I left it noisy.
这样就把那些讨厌的无辜旁观者吓跑了
That way it scares pain-in-the-ass innocent bystanders away.
好了, 你杀了他们两个
All right, you shot them both.
接下来你怎么办?
Now what do you do?
坐下, 把我的晚饭吃完
Sit down, finish my dinner.
来吧, 孩子, 别糊弄了
Come on, kid. Don't fool around.
把你的手垂下, 让枪滑掉
Just let your hand drop to your side and let the gun slip out.
每个人都会认为你还拿着枪
Everybody will still think you got it.
他们会瞪着你的脸, 迈克
They're gonna be staring at your face, Mike
所以快步离开那地方, 但不要跑
so walk out of the place real fast, but you don't run.
不要直视任何人的眼睛, 但也不要把目光移开
Don't look nobody directly in the eye, but don't look away, either.
相信我, 他们会被你吓死的, 所以什么都不用担心
They're gonna be scared stiff of you, believe me,
so don't worry about nothing.
你知道, 你可以全身而退
You know, you're gonna turn out all right.
你去度个长假, 没人知道去哪儿
You take a long vacation, nobody knows where
我们会接住地狱的
and we're gonna catch the hell.
-你觉得后果会有多糟? -非常他妈的糟糕
-How bad do you think it's gonna be? -Pretty goddamn bad.
可能所有的家族会联合起来对付我们
Probably all the other families will line up against us.
没关系
That's all right.
这种事每5年或10年都会发生一次
These things gotta happen every five years or so Ten years.
这有助于清除坏血
Helps to get rid of the bad blood.
上一次到现在已经有10年了
Been ten years since the last one.
你得从一开始就阻止他们
You gotta stop them at the beginning
就像他们应该在慕尼黑阻止希特勒一样
like they should have stopped Hitler at Munich.
他们不该让他得逞的, 他们这是自找麻烦
They should have never let him get away with that.
They was just asking for big trouble.
知道吗, 迈克
You know, Mike
我们都为你感到骄傲, 你是一个英雄
we was all proud of you, being a hero and all.
你父亲也是
Your father too.
没有任何线索, 没有任何迹象, 什么都没有
Nothing. Not a hint. Absolutely nothing.
索洛佐的人也不知道在哪里开会
Even Sollozzo's people don't know where the meeting will be held.
我们还有多少时间?
How much time do we have?
一个半小时后, 他们会在杰克·邓普西的酒吧前接你
They're going to pick you up in front of Jack Dempsey's
joint in an hour and a half. Exactly an hour and a half.
我们可以派人跟踪他们, 看看结果如何
We could put a tail on them, see how it turns out.
索洛佐会在街上乱转, 甩掉我们的人
Sollozzo'll lose our ass going around the block.
谈判的协商人呢?
What about the negotiator?
他在我家和我的几个手下玩皮诺奇纸牌
He's over at my place playing pinochle with a couple of my men.
他很开心, 他们让他赢了
He's happy. They're letting him win.
这对迈克来说太危险了
It's too much of a risk for Mike.
也许我们应该取消, 桑尼
Maybe we ought to call it off, Sonny.
协商人一直在打牌, 直到迈克安然无恙地回来才让他走
The negotiator keeps playing cards until Mike's back safe and sound.
为什么不把车里该死的人都炸了?
Why doesn't he blast who's ever in the goddamn car?
太危险了, 他们会留心的
Too dangerous. They'll be looking for that.
索洛佐可能根本不在车里, 桑尼
Sollozzo might not even be in the car, Sonny.
我来接
I got it.
布朗克斯的路易斯餐厅
Louis Restaurant in the Bronx.
消息可靠吗?
Is it reliable?
这是我在麦克劳斯基警区里的人
That's my man in McCluskey's precinct.
警察巡长必须全天24小时待命
A police captain's got to be on call 24 hours a day.
他在8点到10点之间用那个号码签了名
He signed out at that number between 8:00 and 10:00.
有谁知道那个地方?
Anybody know this joint?
对, 确实, 我知道
Yeah, sure. I do.
对我们太理想了
It's perfect for us.
一个小家庭餐厅, 食物精美
A small family place, good food.
每个人都只关心自己的事, 太完美了
Everyone minds his business. It's perfect.
皮特, 那儿有个旧式马桶
Pete, they got an old-fashioned toilet.
你知道, 就是水箱有吊链的那种
You know, the box and the chain thing.
我们也许可以用胶带把枪粘在它后面
We might be able to tape the gun behind it.
好的, 迈克, 你去了餐厅
All right. Mike, you go to the restaurant
你吃点东西, 聊会儿天, 放松一下
You eat, you talk for a while, you relax.
也可以让他们放松下来
You make them relax.
然后你站起来去上厕所
Then you get up and go take a leak.
不, 更好的办法是, 你先征求对方同意再去
No, better still, you ask for permission to go.
当你回来的时候, 就开枪
And when you come back, you come out blasting.
不要心存侥幸, 每人头上各开2枪
And don't take any chances. Two shots in the head apiece.
听着, 我的意思是, 我要一个好手去藏枪
listen. I want somebody good,
and I mean very good to plant that gun.
我不希望我弟弟出来时手无寸铁
I don't want him coming out with just his dick in his hands.
枪会在那里的
The gun will be there.
好吧, 听着, 你开车送他, 事后再接他回来
All right, listen. You drive him and you pick him up after the job.
来吧, 我们行动
Come on. Let's move.
他告诉过你事成之后立刻丢枪了吗?
Did he tell you to drop the gun right away?
说了, 上百万次了
Yeah, a million times.
切记, 你一出门就朝每人头上各开2枪
Don't forget, two shots apiece
in the head as soon as you come out the door.
你们认为要多久我才能回家?
How long do you think it'll be before I can come back?
至少得一年, 迈克
At least a year, Mike.
听着, 我会和妈妈说清楚, 你临走前不能去看她...
Listen, I'll square with Mom you not seeing her before you leave...
时机成熟时, 我会告诉你的女朋友
and I'll get a message to that girlfriend when the time is right.
保重
Take care.
再见, 迈克
See you, Mike.
我很高兴你来了, 迈克
I'm glad you came, Mike.
我希望我们能把一切都弄清楚
I hope we can straighten everything out.
这太可怕了, 根本不是我想要的结果
This is terrible. It's not the way I wanted things to go at all.
根本不应该发生这种事的
It should have never happened.
我想今晚把一切都弄清楚
I want to straighten everything out tonight.
我不想让我父亲再烦恼了
I don't want my father bothered anymore.
他不会的, 迈克
He won't be, Mike.
我以我的孩子们发誓他不会的
I swear on my children he won't be.
不过我们谈话的时候, 你得坦诚才行
But you got to keep an open mind when we talk.
我希望你不像你哥哥桑尼那样急性子
I hope you're not a hothead like your brother Sonny.
简直不能和他谈生意
You can't talk business with him.
(意大利语)
他是个好孩子
He's a good kid.
那晚的事我很抱歉, 迈克
I'm sorry about the other night, Mike.
我得搜你的身, 转过身来, 好吗?
I gotta frisk you, so turn around, huh?
跪在椅子上, 面向我
On your knees, facing me.
我想我干这行已经嫌老了
I guess I'm getting too old for my job.
太暴躁了
Too grouchy.
受不了别人的激怒, 你知道是怎么回事
Can't stand the aggravation. You know how it is.
他没带家伙
He's clean.
我们要去泽西岛?
We're going to Jersey?
也许
Maybe.
做得漂亮, 卢
Nice work, Lou.
(路易斯餐厅)
这里的意大利菜味道还可以吧?
How's the Italian food in this restaurant?
很好
Good.
尝尝这里的小牛肉, 是本市最棒的
Try the veal. It's the best in the city.
我点了一份
I'll have it.
快点
Go ahead.
好了
我要和迈克用意大利语交谈
I'm gonna speak Italian to Mike.
请便
Go ahead.
-我很抱歉  -真的吗?
-Mi dispiace. -Sul serio?
你知道我和你父亲之间发生了什么事情, 这是一桩生意
Tu ai sapiri cachiddu ca successe tra
mie tu patri. fu una cosa di bisiness.
我一直很尊敬你父亲, 但你父亲的思想已经过时了
Io ai un grosso rispetto pi tu patri, ma tu patri pensa al'antica.
你必须知道一件事, 我是一个重信义的人
Iddu nu lo vo capiri che eo sono un uomo de onori.
-别和我说这些, 我全明白  -你知道了?
-Non mo diri sti cosi. I sacciu. -'o sai?
可以告诉你, 我已经向塔塔基利亚家族求援了
E tu a sapiri che eo ho aiutato a famiglia Tattaglia.
我认为我们可以达成协议
Io credo che ci potemo mettere in accordo.
我想要和平
Io voglio paci.
忘掉这些仇恨和不快吧
E lasciamo perdere co tutti sti cazzati.
我有个希望...
Ma voggiu ca...
什么?
Che?
你怎么说的?
Come si dice?
对我来说最重要的是
What's most important to me
我得到一个保证: 不会再有人想要我父亲的命
is that I have a guarantee: No more attempts on my father's life.
我能给你什么保证, 迈克?
What guarantees could I give you, Mike?
我是被追捕的那个
I am the hunted one.
我错过了机会
I missed my chance.
你太看重我了, 孩子
You think too much of me, kid.
我没有那么精明
I'm not that clever.
我想要的只是休战
All I want is a truce.
我不得不去一趟厕所, 可以吗?
I have to go to the bathroom. Is that all right?
你想去你就去吧
You gotta go, you gotta go.
我搜过了, 他没带家伙
I frisked him. He's clean.
别去太久
Don't take too long.
我搜过上千个小混混了
I've frisked a thousand young punks.
-感觉好多了吗?  -是
-Ti senti meglio? -Si.
迈克尔, 你明白我的意思吧?
Micheluzzo, tu mi capisci, no?
是的, 意大利人, 就像你父亲
Si italiano, come tu patri.
你父亲病了
Tu patri sta male.
等他感觉好些的时候, 让我们联合起来, 把所有事情做好
Quand' iddu sta meglio, cicchiamo di fare
un union e mettiamo tuttto a posto.
这一切都结束了
Sti fisseria si deve a finì.
(警方追捕警察杀手)
(本市黑道瓦解)
(警察副巡长与毒贩勾结)
(黑社会头子巴西尼接受警方盘问)
(黑社会大火并)
(黑社会大亨维托·柯里昂返家)
嘿, 过来
Hey, come on.
乔, 你接手
Joe, you take over.
我爱你, 爷爷
I love you, Grandpa.
对不起, 爸, 他还不认识你
I'm sorry, Pa. He doesn't know you yet.
给你, 大块头, 念给爷爷听
Here you are, big guy. Give it to Grandpa.
好, "我祝你早日康复, 爷爷, 我希望能快点见到你
Okay. "I hope you get well, Grandpa, and I wish I would see you soon.
"爱你的孙子, 弗兰克"
"Love your grandson, Frank."
哦, 谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
和你妈妈一起去吧
Go with your mother.
去吧, 把他们带到楼下去
Go ahead. Take 'em downstairs.
妈妈
Mom
走吧, 卡洛, 你也是
Go on, Carlo. You too.
走吧
Go on.
亲爱的, 我给你准备了炖鸡
I got chicken cacciatore for you, sweetheart.
但你能吃多少呢?
But how much can you eat?
你怎么了, 卡洛?
What's the matter with you, Carlo?
闭嘴, 摆好桌子吧
Shut up and set the table.
自从麦克劳斯基被杀后
Since McCluskey's killing
警方一直在打击我们的大部分行动
the police have been cracking down on most of our operations.
其它的家族也是一样
And also the other families'.
牺牲很多
Been a lot of bad blood.
他们打击我们
They hit us
所以我们反击了他们
so we hit them back.
通过我们在报社中的联系人, 我们提供了不少内幕
Through our contacts in the newspapers,
we've been able to put out a lot of material
很多麦克劳斯基跟毒贩索洛佐在毒品交易中勾结的事
about McCluskey being linked with Sollozzo in the drug rackets.
所以, 情况开始缓和了
See, things are starting to loosen up.
爸爸, 我要派弗雷多去拉斯维加斯
Dad, I'm sending Fredo to Las Vegas
洛杉矶的弗朗西斯科阁下会给予他保护
under the protection of Don Francesco of L.A.
我想让他休息一阵
I want him to rest.
-我要去学赌场的业务了  -是
-I'm going to learn the casino business. -Yeah.
迈克尔在哪儿?
Where is Michael?
迈克尔杀了索洛佐
It was Michael who killed Sollozzo.
不过他很安全
But he's safe.
我们正在着手把他弄回来
We're starting to work to bring him back now.
我要你找出塔塔基里亚这个皮条客的藏身之处
I want you to find out where that little pimp Tattaglia is hiding.
我现在就想要他的命, 马上!
I want his ass now. right now!
-嘿, 桑尼  -什么事?
-Hey, Sonny. -What?
现在局势刚刚缓和下来
Things are starting to loosen up a little bit.
你要是去追塔塔基利亚
If you go after Tattaglia
又会引起一场大战
all hell's going to break loose.
让烟雾散去吧, 爸爸可以谈判
Let the smoke clear. Pop can negotiate.
不, 爸爸在身体好转之前什么都不能做
No, Pop can't do nothing till he's better.
我要决定...
I'm gonna decide...
好吧, 但你的战争让我们损失了很多钱
All right, but your war's costing us a lot of money.
没有任何进帐, 我们不能做生意了
Nothing's coming in. We can't do business.
他们也不能做生意, 别担心
Neither can they. Don't worry about it.
-我们不能陷入僵局  -好吧, 不会再有僵局了
-We can't afford a stalemate. -Well, there ain't no more stalemate.
我要以宰了那个老混蛋来结束这一切
I'm gonna end it by killing that old bastard.
是啊, 你现在名声大噪, 我希望你喜欢
Yeah, you're getting a great reputation. I hope you're enjoying it.
你就照我说的去做!
You just do what I tell you to do!
该死的! 如果我有一个西西里人的战时军师
Goddamn it! If I had a wartime consigliere a Sicilian
我就不会落到这种地步了!
I wouldn't be in this shape!
爸爸有杰安可, 看看我有什么
Pop had Genco. Look what I got.
对不起, 我不是那个意思
I'm sorry. I didn't mean that.
妈妈做了一顿小小的晚餐, 今天是礼拜日
Mom made a little dinner. It's Sunday.
黑鬼对我们哈林区的银行新政策非常满意
Niggers are having a good time with our policy banks up there in Harlem.
开着新凯迪拉克, 我先帮他们付一半的钱
Driving them new Cadillacs, paying 50% on a bet.
从他们开始赚钱时, 我就知道会发生这种事
I knew that was gonna happen as soon as they started making big money.
爸爸从来不在餐桌上 当着孩子们谈生意
Papa never talked business at the table in front of the kids.
-闭嘴, 康妮  -你永远不要告诉她闭嘴, 明白了吗?
-Shut up, Connie. -Don't you ever tell her to shut up. You got that?
桑蒂诺, 不要干预
Santino, don't interfere.
桑尼, 汤姆, 吃过饭后我想与你们谈谈
Sonny, Tom, I'd like to talk to you, maybe after dinner.
-我本可以为这个家庭做更多的事...  -我们不在餐桌上讨论生意
-I could be doing more for the family...
-We don't discuss business at the table.
我向你致敬, 汤玛西诺阁下
迈克
你为什么离房子那么远?
你知道万一你出了事, 我要向你父亲负责的
保镖们都在这儿
还是十分危险
我听纽约的桑蒂诺说的
你的敌人知道你在这儿了
桑蒂诺有没有说我什么时候能回去?
嗯, 还不行
目前是不可能的
谢谢
你现在要去哪里?
柯里昂村
坐我的车去
不, 我想走路
小心点
迈克尔, 柯里昂村到了
所有的男人都到哪儿去了?
他们全都在战争中死了
嘿, 这里是战死者的姓名
我的上帝, 好一个美女
你好像中邪了一样
迈克尔
在西西里, 女人比猎枪还危险
打猎有收收获吗?
你认识这一带所有的女孩吗?
我们看到几位真正的美人
其中一位让我们的朋友触电了
她可真够风骚了
她全身上下都很美
那么漂亮的头发, 嘴
这一带的女孩都很美, 而且很贞洁
这个穿着紫色衣服
头发上绑着紫色的缎带
看起来像希腊人, 而非意大利人
你认识她吗?
不!
在本镇没有那样子的女孩!
我的天, 我明白了
有什么不对劲儿的地方吗?
我们走
是他女儿
叫他出来
不, 不, 叫他出来
法布利奇欧, 你来翻译
好的, 先生
如果我冒犯了你, 我深表歉意
I apologize if I offended you.
我对这个地方很陌生
I'm a stranger in this country
我无意冒犯你和你的女儿
and I meant no disrespect to you or your daughter.
我是一个躲在西西里的美国人
I'm an American hiding in Sicily.
我的名字是迈克尔·柯里昂
My name is Michael Corleone.
有人愿意花大价钱买这条信息
There are people who would pay a lot of money for that information.
但那样你女儿就会失去父亲…
But then your daughter would lose a father...
而不是得到一位丈夫
instead of gaining a husband.
我想见见你的女儿
I want to meet your daughter
在你的允许下
with your permission
并在你的家人的监督之下
and under the supervision of your family.
我是真诚的
with all respect.
星期天早上到我家来, 我叫维提
谢谢
她叫什么名字?
艾波洛妮亚
Apollonia.
很美的名字
这是我女儿, 艾波洛妮亚
这位是迈克尔·柯里昂先生
谢谢
我会把你打晕
I'll knock you dizzy.
废话少说
Save it for the library.
来吧, 我们得去接我妹妹. 走吧
Come on. We've got to pick up my sister. Let's go.
怎么了? 嗯?
What's the matter? Huh?
怎么了?
What's the matter?
-这是我的错!  -他在哪儿?
-It was my fault! -Where is he?
桑尼, 求你了. 这是我的错
Sonny, please. It was my fault.
桑尼, 是我的错. 我打了他, 是我先开始打他的
Sonny, It was my fault. I hit him. I started a fight with him.
是我先开始打他的. 我打了他, 所以他打了我...
I started a fight with him. I hit him, so he hit me...
好吧. 我去找个医生来给你检查一下
Okay. I'm just gonna get a doctor to come and take a look at you.
桑尼, 求求你别动手. 求求你别动手
Sonny, please don't do anything. please don't do anything.
你是怎么了? 我会怎么办?
What's the matter with you? What am I gonna do?
我会在孩子出生之前让他成为孤儿吗? 嗯?
Am I gonna make that baby an orphan before he's born? Huh? Hmm?
好了吗?
All right?
还在把赌注押在洋基队上吗?
Still betting the Yankees pretty heavy?
告诉他别再投注了, 好吗?
Tell him to stop taking action, all right?
你上周末输给我的钱够多了
You lost enough money last weekend to me.
卡洛, 过来, 过来, 过来!
Carlo, Come here, come here, come here!
你再碰我妹妹一下, 我就杀了你
You touch my sister again, I'll kill you.
(意大利语)
嘿! 没想到你会来, 凯. 你应该先打个电话来
Hey! Weren't expecting you. Kay. You should call.
是的, 我打了. 我写过信也打过电话
Yes, well, I have. I've tried writing and calling.
我想联系迈克尔
Now, I wanna reach Michael.
没有人知道他在哪儿
Nobody knows where he is.
我们知道他没事, 但仅此而已
We know he's all right, but that's all.
-怎么了?  -那是个意外. 但没有人受伤
-What was that? -That's an accident. But nobody was hurt.
汤姆
Tom
请你把这封信交给迈克尔, 好吗?
Would you give this letter to Michael, please?
如果我接受了, 在法庭上
If I accepted that, in a court of law
他们可以证明我知道他的下落
they could prove I have knowledge of his whereabouts.
现在你只要耐心一点, 凯. 他会和你联系的, 好吗?
Now you just be patient, Kay. He'll get in touch with you, all right?
我让我的出租车走了, 我是否能进去打电话叫一辆?
I let my cab go, so can I come in to call another one, please?
来吧, 对不起. 来吧
Come on. I'm sorry. Come on.
你好? 喂?
Hello? Hello?
卡洛在吗?
Is Carlo there?
-你是谁? -我是卡洛的朋友
-Who's this? -This is a friend of Carlo's.
你能告诉他我今晚不能去了吗?
Would you tell him that I can't make it tonight until later?
婊子
Bitch.
-晚饭在桌上  -我还不饿
-Dinner's on the table. -I'm not hungry yet.
-你的食物在桌子上, 快变凉了. -我一会儿出去吃
Your food is on the table. It's getting cold. -I'll eat out later.
你叫我给你做晚饭的
You told me to make you dinner.
-嘿, 去你妈的, 嗯? -我去你妈的!
-Hey, vaffancolo, eh? -I'll vaffanculo you!
她的嘴很脏, 这个意大利婊子
She has a filthy mouth, this little guinea brat.
就是这样. 都打碎吧
That's it. Break it all
你这个被宠坏的婊子, 都打碎吧
you spoiled guinea brat. Break it all!
为什么不把你的婊子带回家吃晚饭?
Why don't you bring your whore home for dinner?
也许我会. 有什么不行的?
Maybe I will. Why not?
现在把它清干净!
Now clean it up!
我才不清!
Like hell I will!
清干净, 你这个被宠坏的婊子
Clean it up, you guinea spoiled brat!
把它清干净! 我说把它清干净!
Clean it up! I said, Clean it up!
把它清干净! 把它清干净!
Clean it up! Clean it up!
不!
No!
你这个婊子养的!
You son of a bitch!
清干净!
Clean it!
把它清干净!
Clean it up.
对, 对. 来, 杀了我! 像你爸一样当凶手!
Yeah, yeah. Come on, now! Kill me! Be a murderer like your father!
来吧! 你们柯里昂家族的人都是杀人犯!  -我恨你!
-Come on! All you Corleones are murderers! -I hate you!
-来吧, 杀了我! -我要杀了你!
-Come on! kill me! -I'll kill you!
来吧, 杀了我! 起来! 滚出去!
Come on, kill me! Get up! Get out of here!
-我恨你!-现在我要杀你了
-I hate you! -Now I'll kill you.
你这意大利贱货
You guinea brat, you.
滚出来
Get out here!
康妮, 怎么回事?
Connie, what's the matter?
我听不见你说的, 什么事?
I can't hear you. What is it?
康妮, 说大点声. 孩子在哭
Connie, talk louder. The baby's crying.
桑蒂诺, 我听不懂. 我不明白
Santino, I can't understand. I don't know.
什么事, 康妮
Yeah, Connie.
听我说, 你在那等着
Listen, you wait there.
不, 你就在那里等着
No, you just wait there.
婊子养的! 婊子养的!
Son of a bitch! Son of a bitch!
-桑尼, 怎么回事? -婊子养的!
-What's the matter, Sonny? -Son of a bitch!
打开该死的大门, 给我滚开
Open the goddamn gate. Get off your ass.
桑尼!
Sonny!
桑尼, 得了吧!
Sonny, come on!
滚开!
Get out of here!
去追他, 跟上
Go after him. Go on.
婊子养的! 快点! 快点!
Son of a bitch. Come on! Come on!
给我一口
Give me a drop.
我太太在楼上哭
My wife is crying upstairs.
我听见汽车到家里来
I hear cars coming to the house.
我的军师
Consigliere of mine
我觉得你应该把大家都知道的事告诉你的头儿
I think you should tell your Don what everyone seems to know.
我什么都没告诉妈妈
I didn't tell Mama anything.
我正要上楼叫醒你, 告诉你
I was about to come up and wake you just now and tell you.
-但你需要先喝一杯  -是
-But you needed a drink first. -Yeah.
现在你喝过酒了
Now you've had your drink.
他们在收费站杀了桑尼
They shot Sonny on the causeway.
他死了
He's dead.
我不要追查此事
I want no inquiries made.
我不想要报复
I want no acts of vengeance.
我要你安排一次会面
I want you to arrange a meeting
与五大家族的族长
with the heads of the five families.
这场火并该终止了
This war stops now.
打电话给包纳萨拉
Call Bonasera.
我们现在需要他了
We need him now.
我是汤姆·哈根
This is Tom Hagen.
我应维托·柯里昂的要求, 打这个电话
I'm calling for Vito Corleone, at his request.
你欠教父的一个人情
Now, you owe your Don a service
他相信你会回报他的
he has no doubt that you will repay it.
他在一小时后会到你的殡仪馆去
Now, he will be at your funeral parlor in one hour.
在那儿等候他
Be there to greet him.
我的朋友
Well, my friend
你预备好为我服务了吗?
are you ready to do me this service?
是的, 你想要我做什么?
Yes. What do you want me to do?
我要你尽你一切的力量和技巧, 为他化妆
I want you to use all your powers and all your skills.
我不想让他妈妈看到他这个样子
I don't want his mother to see him this way.
看看他们是怎么屠杀我儿子的
Look how they massacred my boy.
教你英文会安全一点
我会英文, 星期一
Monday
星期二, 星期三, 星期四
Tuesday, Thursday Wednesday
-星期五, 星期日, 星期六 -哦, 好极了
Friday, Sunday, Saturday.
你好, 汤玛西诺阁下
迈克尔在教我开车
我开给你看
家里的一切都还好吧?
年轻人不再尊重任何事了
时代越变越糟
这地方对你已变得太危险了
我要你搬到西拉古莎附近的别墅
有什么不对吗?
从美国传来的坏消息
你哥哥桑蒂诺, 他们杀了他
我们走了, 你答应的
-法布利奇欧 -什么事, 先生?
-Fabrizio. -Yes, sir?
备车
你要自己开吗, 老板?
Are you driving yourself, boss?
是的
Yes.
你太太跟你一起去吗?
Is your wife coming with you?
不, 我想让你带她去她父亲家, 直到我确定安全再说
No, I want you to take her to her father's house till I know things are safe.
好的, 随你吩咐, 老板
Okay, anything you say, boss.
卡罗, 艾波洛妮亚呢?
她想给你个惊喜, 她要开车
她会当个美国好太太
等一下, 我去拿行李
法布利奇欧
你要去哪?
迈克尔, 在那儿等我开过去
不! 不, 艾波洛妮亚!
No! No, Apollonia!
巴西尼阁下
Don Barzini
我要感谢你今天在这里帮助我组织这次会议
I want to thank you for helping me organize this meeting here today.
还有来自纽约和新泽西的其它五大家族的族长
And also the other heads of the five families from New York and New Jersey.
来自布朗克斯的卡迈恩·库尼奥
Carmine Cuneo from the Bronx
来自布鲁克林的
and from Brooklyn
菲利普·塔塔基利亚
Philip Tattaglia.
来自斯塔滕岛的
And from Staten Island
维克多·斯特拉奇
we have with us Victor Strachi.
所有其他从加利福尼亚州、堪萨斯城
And all the other associates that came as
far as from California and Kansas City
和全国其他地区远道而来的同道
and all the other territories of the country.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
事情怎么会发展到这个地步?
How did things ever get so far?
我不知道
I don't know.
太不幸了, 也太没必要了
It was so unfortunate and so unnecessary.
塔塔基利亚失去了一个儿子
Tattaglia lost a son
我失去了一个儿子
and I lost a son.
我们扯平了
We're quits.
如果塔塔基利亚同意
And if Tattaglia agrees
我愿意让事情像以前那样继续下去
then I'm willing to let things go on the way they were before.
我们都很感谢柯里昂阁下 召开这次会议
We are all grateful to Don Corleone for calling this meeting.
我们都了解他是一个有信用的人
We all know him as a man of his word.
他为人谦虚, 总是能讲道理
A modest man. He'll always listen to reason.
是的, 巴西尼阁下
Yes, Don Barzini.
他太谦虚了
He's too modest.
所有的法官和政客都在他的掌控之中
He had all the judges and politicians in his pocket.
他却拒绝与我们分享
He refused to share them.
我什么时候拒绝过和解?
When did I ever refuse an accommodation?
在座的各位都认识我
All of you know me here.
除了一次, 我什么时候拒绝过?
When did I ever refuse, except one time?
为什么?
And why?
因为我相信毒品生意会在未来毁掉我们
Because I believe this drug business is gonna destroy us in the years to come.
我的意思是, 这不像赌博、酗酒, 甚至不像女人
I mean, it's not like gambling or liquor or even women
这些是现在大多数人想要的东西
which is something that most people want nowadays
只是被教会的牧师禁止而己
and is forbidden to them by the pezzonovante of the church.
即使是过去在赌博和其他事情上帮助过我们的警察部门
Even the police departments that have helped us
in the past with gambling and other things
在毒品问题上也会拒绝帮助我们
are gonna refuse to help us when it comes to narcotics.
我当时相信, 现在仍然相信
And I believed that then and I believe that now.
时代变了
Times have changed.
现在不像以前了
It's not like the old days
我们可以做任何我们想做的事
when we could do anything we want.
拒绝不是朋友的行为
A refusal is not the act of a friend.
柯里昂阁下握有全纽约法律界以及政客的势力
If Don Corleone had all the judges and politicians in New York
他就必须与大家分享, 让大家都能利用他们
then he must share them or let others use them.
他必须让我们从井中取水
He must let us draw the water from the well.
当然, 他可以为这些服务提出账单
Certainly, he can present a bill for such services.
毕竟, 我们不是共产党人
After all, we are not Communists.
我同样也不相信毒品
I also don't believe in drugs.
多年来, 我给我的人额外的报酬
For years, I paid my people extra
所以他们不会做这种生意
so they wouldn't do that kind of business.
避免有人来找他们说"我有白粉
Somebody comes to them and says, "I have powders.
"你只要投资3000元到4000元
"If you put up a three, four-thousand-dollar investment
"我们就可以赚到5万元"
"we can make 50,000 distributing."
他们怎能抗拒得了
So they can't resist.
我想把它作为一项业务来控制, 让它保持体面
I want to control it as a business, to keep it respectable.
我不要它们接近学校
I don't want it near schools
我不要把它们卖给孩子
I don't want it sold to children.
这是一种耻辱
That's an infamia.
在我的城市, 我只想在黑人, 有色人种中流通
In my city, we'll keep the traffic in the dark people, the colored.
反正他们是动物, 就让他们失去灵魂吧
They're animals anyway, so let them lose their souls.
我希望我们到这儿来能一起讨论
I hoped that we could come here and reason together.
身为一个讲道理的人
As a reasonable man
我愿意做任何必要的事情来找到和平解决这些问题的办法
I'm willing to do whatever's necessary to find
a peaceful solution to these problems.
那么我们同意了
Then we are agreed.
毒品生意可以做但要有限制
The traffic in drugs will be permitted but controlled.
柯里昂阁下会给我们东部的保护
Don Corleone will give us protection in the east
而且会有和平
and there will be the peace.
但我必须有柯里昂阁下的确切保证
But I must have strict assurance from Corleone.
随着时间的推移, 他的地位越来越强
As time goes by and his position becomes stronger
他会试图进行个人报复吗?
will he attempt any individual vendetta?
听着, 我们都是讲道理的人
Look, we are all reasonable men here.
我们不必像律师一样给出保证
We don't have to give assurances as if we were lawyers.
你谈到复仇
You talk about vengeance.
复仇能让你的儿子复活吗?
Is vengeance gonna bring your son back to you?
或者我的儿子复活?
Or my boy to me?
我放弃为我儿子复仇
I forego the vengeance of my son.
但我有个自私的要求
But I have selfish reasons.
我最小的儿子因为索洛佐的生意
My youngest son was forced to leave this country
被迫离开这个国家
because of this Sollozzo business.
好吧. 我必须安排
All right. And I have to make arrangements
让他安全的回来, 洗脱所有这些虚假指控
to bring him back here safely, cleared of all these false charges.
而我是个迷信的人
But I'm a superstitious man.
如果他遭遇了什么不幸的意外
And if some unlucky accident should befall him
如果他被警察开枪打死
if he should get shot in the head by a police officer
或者他在牢房里上吊自杀
or if he should hang himself in his jail cell
或者他被闪电击中
or if he's struck by a bolt of lightening
那么我会责怪这个房间里的一些人
then I'm going to blame some of the people in this room.
到那时候, 我不会原谅
And that I do not forgive.
除此以外
But that aside
我以我孙子们的灵魂发誓
let me say that I swear on the souls of my grandchildren
我不会是那个破坏我们今天在这里建立的和平的人
that I will not be the one to break the peace we've made here today.
当我与塔塔基里亚人会面时, 我应该
When I meet with the Tattaglia people, should I insist
坚持所有这些毒品中间人都没有犯罪记录吗?
that all these drug middlemen have clean records?
提出来无妨, 不要坚持
Mention it. Don't insist.
巴西尼这种人, 不用你说他也明白
Barzini is a man who'll know that without being told.
你是说塔塔基利亚
You mean Tattaglia.
塔塔基利亚是个皮条客
Tattaglia's a pimp.
他没本事干掉桑蒂诺
He never could've outfought Santino.
直到今天我才知道, 一直以来
But I didn't know until this day that it was
都是巴西尼在主使
Barzini all along.
来吧, 南希
Come on, Nancy.
大家紧跟在一起. 布莱恩?
Keep together, everyone. Brian?
好的
All right.
你回来多久了?
How long have you been back?
我回来一年了
I've been back a year.
我想还不止
Longer than that, I think.
很高兴见到你, 凯
It's good to see you, Kay.
我现在为我父亲工作
I'm working for my father now.
他病了, 病得很重
He's been sick.Very sick.
但是你不像他, 迈克尔
But you're not like him, Michael.
我以为你不会成为你爸爸那样的人
I thought you weren't going to become a man like your father.
这是你告诉我的
That's what you told me.
我父亲和其他有权势的人没有什么不同
My father's no different than any other powerful man.
就是那种要对他人负责任的人
Any man who's responsible for other people.
就像参议员或总统一样
Like a senator or a president.
你知道你这话听起来有多天真吗?
Do you know how naive you sound?
为什么
Why?
参议员和总统不会杀人
Senators and presidents don't have men killed.
哦
Oh.
谁天真了, 凯?
Who's being naive, Kay?
凯, 我父亲做事的方式已经结束了. 过时了
Kay, my father's way of doing things is over. It's finished.
连他自己都知道
Even he knows that.
我的意思是, 再过5年柯里昂家族
I mean, in five years the Corleone family
会完全合法化
is going to be completely legitimate.
相信我
Trust me.
关于我的生意, 我只能告诉你这些
That's all I can tell you about my business.
凯...
Kay...
迈克尔, 你为什么来这里?
Michael, Why did you come here?
为什么?
Why?
过了这么久, 你想要我做什么?
What do you want with me after all this time?
你不打电话也不写信
Without even calling or writing.
我来这里是因为我需要你. 因为我在乎你
I came here because I need you. Because I care for you.
-别再说了, 迈克尔  -因为...
-Please stop it, Michael. -Because...
我要你嫁给我
I want you to marry me.
太晚了, 太晚了
It's too late. It's too late.
请求你, 凯...
Please, Kay...
我愿意做任何事来弥补我们之间发生的一切
I'll do anything you ask to make up for what's happened to us.
因为这很重要, 凯
Because that's important, Kay.
因为重要的是
Because what's important is that
我们拥有彼此
we have each other.
我们要共度一生
That we have a life together.
我们会有孩子
That we have children.
我们的孩子
Our children.
凯
Kay.
我需要你
I need you.
而且我爱你
and I love you.
巴西尼的人抢了我的地盘
Barzini's people chisel my territory
而我们却无动于衷!
and we do nothing about it!
很快, 布鲁克林就没有一个地方可以让我落脚了!
Soon, there won't be one place in Brooklyn I can hang my hat!
耐心点儿
Just be patient.
我不是求你帮忙, 只是不想受掣肘
I'm not askin' you for help. Just take off the handcuffs.
要有耐心
Be patient.
我们必须保护自己
We gotta protect ourselves.
给我个机会再招募一些新人
Give me a chance to recruit some new men.
不行
No.
-我不想给巴西尼一个开战的借口  -迈克尔, 你错了
-I don't wanna give Barzini an excuse to start fighting.
-Mike, you're wrong.
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone,
你曾说过, 有一天泰西欧和我可以组建我们自己的家族
you once said the day would come when
Tessio and me could form our own family.
今天以前我想都不敢想
Till today, I would never think of it.
我必须征得你的许可
I must ask your permission.
迈克尔现在是一家之主
Well, Michael is now head of the family and
如果他允许, 那么我就祝福你
if he gives his permission, then you have my blessing.
等我们搬到内华达州之后
After we make the move to Nevada
你就可以脱离柯里昂家族自立门户了
you can break off from the Corleone family and go on your own.
在我们搬到内华达州之后
After we make the move to Nevada.
那得花多长时间?
How long will that be?
6个月
Six months.
原谅我, 教父
Forgive me, Godfather
当你离开之后
but with you gone
我和皮特迟早会受到巴西尼的控制
me and Pete'll come under Barzini's thumb sooner or later.
我恨那个该死的巴西尼
And I hate that goddamn Barzini.
6个月之后, 就没有什么可以组建的家族了
In six months' time, there won't be nothing left to build on.
你相信我的判断吗?
You have faith in my judgment?
相信
Yes.
我有你的忠诚吗?
Do I have your loyalty?
是的, 一直都有, 教父
Yes, always, Godfather.
那就做迈克尔的朋友
Then be a friend to Michael.
照他说的去做
Do as he says.
现在有些事情正在谈判中
There are things being negotiated now that are gonna
可以解决你们所有的问题, 回答你们所有的疑问
solve all your problems and answer all your questions.
目前我只能这么告诉你们
That's all I can tell you now.
卡洛, 你在内华达长大的
Carlo, you grew up in Nevada.
我们搬到那里后, 你就是我的得力助手
When we make our move there, you're gonna be my right-hand man.
汤姆·哈根不再做军师了
Tom Hagen's no longer consigliere.
他将会担任我们在拉斯维加斯的律师
He's gonna be our lawyer in Vegas.
这不是对汤姆的不满, 但这是我想要的
That's no reflection on Tom, but that's the way I want it.
此外, 如果我需要帮助, 有谁比我父亲更适合当军师呢?
Besides, if I ever need help,
who's a better consigliere than my father?
就是这样
Well, that's it.
-谢谢, 爸爸  -我为你高兴, 卡洛
-Thank you, Papa. -I'm happy for you, Carlo.
迈克尔... 为什么我出局了?
Mike... Why am I out?
你不适合做乱局中的军师, 汤姆
You're not a wartime consigliere, Tom.
我们正在尝试的搬家可能会让事情变得棘手
Things may get rough with the move we're trying.
汤姆
Tom
我向迈克尔建议过
I advised Michael.
我从不认为你不适合做军师
I never thought you were a bad consigliere.
我认为桑蒂诺不适合当家
I thought Santino was a bad Don
愿他安息
rest in peace.
迈克尔拥有我完全的信任, 和你一样
Michael has all my confidence, as you do.
但是
But
不让你参与即将发生的事情, 是有理由的
there are reasons why you must have no part of what is going to happen.
也许我能帮上忙
Maybe I could help.
你出局了, 汤姆
You're out, Tom
我实在无法不去注意你的脸
I can't get over the way your face looks.
它的确看起来很棒
It really looks good.
这个医生的功夫确实不错
This doctor did some job.
是凯说服你去的吗?
Who talked you into it, Kay?
嘿, 嘿, 等等. 把它们留在这儿
Hey, hey, wait. Leave them out here.
我们待会再处理它们
We'll deal with them later.
他累了, 他想整理一下, 好吗?
He's tired. He wants to clean up. All right.
现在, 让我来开门, 好吗?
Now, let me open the door, all right?
你好, 迈克. 欢迎光临拉斯维加斯
Hello, Mike. Welcome to Las Vegas.
都是为你准备的, 兄弟. 嗯?
All for you, kid. Huh?
全是他的主意, 对吧?
It was all his idea, right?
你的哥哥弗雷多
Well, your brother, Freddy.
你弄来的... 女孩子?
It was... Girls?
-弗雷多...  -嗯?
-Fredo... -Huh?
我马上回来, 你先招呼一下
I'll be right back. You keep them occupied.
-太棒了, 是吧? 你要什么全都有, 兄弟 -那些女孩子是谁?
-Atta boy, huh? Anything you want, kid. -Who are the girls?
那就等你去发现了
That's for you to find out.
把她们赶走, 弗雷多
Get rid of them, Fredo.
嘿, 迈克...
Hey, Mike...
弗雷多, 我是来这儿办公事的
Fredo, I'm here on business.
我明天就走. 马上把她们赶走. 我累了
I leave tomorrow. Now, get rid of them. I'm tired.
把乐队也赶走
Get rid of the band too.
嘿, 取消了. 快点儿, 走吧
Hey, just take off. Come on. Let's go.
嘿, 就这样. 安吉洛, 就是这样. 走吧
Hey, that's it. Angelo, that's it. Let's go.
嘿, 快点儿! 快滚!
Hey, come on! Scram!
快点儿, 亲爱的. 走吧
Come on, honey. Let's go.
我不知道, 强尼
I don't know, Johnny.
我不知道他到底怎么了, 对不起
I don't know what the hell's the matter with him. I'm sorry.
没关系, 弗雷迪
It's all right, Freddy.
我不知道. 他大概累了, 有点过激
I don't know. He's tired, he's hot.
莫·格林呢?
What happened to Moe Greene?
他说他有生意要做
He said he had some business.
他说聚会开始时给他打个电话
He said give him a call when the party started.
好吧, 给他打个电话
Well, give him a call.
强尼, 你好吗?
Johnny, how are you?
你好, 迈克. 再见到你真高兴
Hello, Mike. Nice to see you again.
我们都为你感到骄傲
We're all proud of you.
谢谢, 迈克
Thanks, Mike.
坐, 强尼. 我要跟你谈谈
Sit down, Johnny. I want to talk to you.
老头子也为你感到骄傲, 强尼
The Don's proud of you too, Johnny.
我的一切都归功于他
I owe it all to him.
他知道你有多感激他
Well, he knows how grateful you are.
这就是为什么他想请你帮忙的原因
That's why he'd like to ask a favor of you.
迈克, 我能做什么?
Mike, what can I do?
柯里昂家族正在考虑放弃在橄榄油行业的生意
The Corleone family is thinking of giving up
all its interests in the olive oil business
在这里安顿下来
settling out here.
莫·格林将把他在赌场和酒店的股份卖给我们
Now, Moe Greene will sell us his share of the casino and hotel
使得家族能拥有全部的生意
so it can be completely owned by the family.
汤姆!
Tom!
迈克, 这点你确定吗?
Mike, are you sure about that?
莫很爱这门生意
Moe loves the business.
他从未对我提过要卖掉它的事
He never said nothin' to me about sellin'.
我会给他一个他无法拒绝的提议
I'll make him an offer he can't refuse.
看, 强尼
See, Johnny...
我们认为娱乐将是吸引赌徒进入赌场的一个重要因素
See, we figure that entertainment will be a big
factor in drawing gamblers to the casino.
我们希望你能签署一份合同, 一年来这儿登台5次
And we hope you'll sign a contract to appear five times a year.
也许可以说服你在电影圈中的一些朋友也这么做
Perhaps convince some of your friends in the movies to do the same.
我们指望着你
We're counting on you.
应该的, 迈克
Sure, Mike.
我愿意为我的教父做任何事. 你知道的
I'll do anything for my godfather. You know that.
很好
Good.
嘿, 迈克. 各位好
Hey, Mike. Hello, fellas.
大家都在这. 弗雷多, 汤姆
Everybody's here. Freddy, Tom.
-很高兴见到你, 迈克  -你好吗, 莫?
-Good to see you, Mike. How are you, Moe?
你点的菜都到齐了吗?
Did you got everything you want?
厨师为你做了特色菜
The chef cooked for you special
舞蹈会让你把舌头伸出来, 你的信用很好
the dancers will kick your tongue out and your credit is good.
给屋子里的每个人都弄点筹码来, 他们可以在房间里玩了
Draw chips for everybody in the room so they can play on the house.
我的信用好到可以买下你的股份吗?
My credit good enough to buy you out?
买断我的股份?
Buy me out?
赌场和酒店
The casino. The hotel.
柯里昂家族想买下你全部的股份
The Corleone family wants to buy you out.
柯里昂家族想买下我全部的股份?
The Corleone family wants to buy me out?
不, 我可以买下你的股份, 你不能买断我的股份
No, I buy you out. You don't buy me out.
你的赌场在赔钱
Your casino loses money.
也许我们可以经营得更好
Maybe we can do better.
你认为我在走下坡路了, 迈克?
You think I'm skimming off the top, Mike?
你运气不好
You're unlucky.
你他妈的别让我笑了
You goddamn guineas really make me laugh.
在你们倒霉的时候
I do you a favor and take Freddy in
我帮你们的忙, 收留了弗雷迪
when you're having a bad time
现在你却想把我赶出去!
and now you try to push me out!
慢着
Wait a minute.
你收留弗雷迪
You took Freddy in
是因为柯里昂家族资助了你的赌场
because the Corleone family bankrolled your casino
因为海滨的莫伦纳里家族
because the Molinari family
保证了他的安全
on the coast guaranteed his safety.
现在, 我们在谈正事. 我们谈谈生意吧
Now, we're talkin' business. Let's talk business.
好, 我们来谈生意, 迈克
Yeah, let's talk business, Mike.
首先, 你们都完蛋了
First of all, you're all done.
柯里昂家族已经没有那么强大的力量了
The Corleone family don't have that kind of muscle anymore.
教父生病了, 对吧?
The Godfather's sick, right?
你们正在被巴西尼和其它家族赶出纽约
You're getting chased out of New York by Barzini and the other families.
你以为这里是什么?
What do you think going on here?
你觉得你可以来我的酒店接手吗?
You think you can come to my hotel and take over?
我和巴西尼谈过了
I talked to Barzini.
我可以和他做一笔交易
I can make a deal with him
仍然能保住我的酒店
and still keep my hotel.
这就是你在大庭广众之下扇我哥哥耳光的原因吗?
Is that why you slapped my brother around in public?
啊, 不, 那没什么, 迈克
Ah, no, that was nothing, Mike.
莫也不是故意的
Moe didn't mean nothin' by that.
当然他偶尔也会发脾气
Sure he flies off the handle once in a while
但莫和我, 我们是好朋友, 对吧莫, 嗯?
but Moe and me, we're good friends, right Moe, huh?
我是在做事业
I got a business to run.
有时候我得狠揍他才能让事情顺利
I gotta kick asses sometimes to make it run right.
发生了一点争执, 弗雷迪和我
We had a little argument, Freddy and I
所以我不得不把他摆正
so I had to straighten him out.
你把我哥哥摆正?
You straightened my brother out?
他一次撞了两个鸡尾酒女招待!
He was banging cocktail waitresses two at a time!
弄得客人喝酒没人送
Players couldn't get a drink.
你是怎么回事?
What's wrong with you?
我明天回纽约
I leave for New York tomorrow.
你考虑一个价钱吧
Think about a price.
你知道我是谁吗? 我是莫·格林
Do you know who I am? I'm Moe Greene.
我是在你和拉拉队员约会的时候出道的
I made my bones when you were going out with cheerleaders.
等一下, 莫.  莫, 我有个主意
Wait a minute, Moe. Moe, I got an idea.
汤姆, 你是军师
Tom, you're the consigliere.
你可以和教父谈. 你可以解释...
You can talk to the Don. You can explain...
慢着, 老头子已经半退休了
Just a minute. The Don is semiretired.
迈克现在负责业务
Mike is in charge of the business now.
你有话就向迈克尔说吧
If you have anything to say, say it to Michael.
迈克尔, 你不能来到拉斯维加斯
Mike, You don't come to Las Vegas
和莫·格林那样的人这么说话!
and talk to a man like Moe Greene like that!
弗雷多... 你是我哥哥, 我爱你
Fredo... You're my older brother, and I love you.
但别再和任何人站在一起反对自己的家族
But don't ever take sides with anyone against the family again.
任何时候
Ever.
我必须去看看我父亲和他的手下人
I have to see my father and his people.
你们先吃饭吧
Have dinner without me.
哦, 迈克尔
Oh, Michael.
这个周末我们要出去, 我们要去城里
This weekend we'll go out. We'll go to the city.
-我们去看演出, 然后吃晚餐. 我保证  -嗯
We'll see a show and have dinner. I promise. -Mmm.
哦, 迈克, 迈克
Oh, Michael., Michael
你姐姐想问你点事
Your sister wants to ask you something.
-让她问吧  -她不敢
-Let her ask. -She's afraid to.
康妮和卡洛想让你做他们孩子的教父
Connie and Carlo want you to be godfather to their little boy.
-我们再说吧  -你会吗?
-We'll see. -Will you?
让我考虑一下, 到时再说. 来吧
Let me think about it. We'll see. Come on.
所以… 巴西尼会先对付你
So... Barzini will move against you first.
他会找个你绝对信任的人来安排见面
He'll set up a meeting with someone that you absolutely trust
并保证你的安全
guaranteeing your safety.
但你一出席会议, 他就杀了你
And at that meeting, you'll be assassinated.
我现在比以前爱喝酒了
I like to drink wine more than I used to.
而且越爱喝就喝得越多
Anyway, I'm drinking more.
这对你有好处, 爸爸
It's good for you, Pop.
我不知道
I don't know.
你的妻子和孩子, 你和他们在一起快乐吗?
Your wife and children, are you happy with them?
非常快乐
Very happy.
这样很好
That's good.
我希望你不介意我… 我一直在谈巴西尼的事
I hope you don't mind the way I...
I keep going over this Barzini business.
不, 一点也不
No, not at all.
这是我的老习惯
It's an old habit.
我一生都在努力不让自己粗心大意
I spent my life tryin' not to be careless.
女人和孩子可以粗心大意, 但男人不行
Women and children can be careless, but not men.
-你儿子怎么样?  -很好
-How's your boy? -He's good.
你知道, 他越来越像你了
You know, he looks more like you every day.
他比我聪明
He's smarter than I am.
才3岁, 就看得懂漫画了
Three years old, he can read the funny papers.
他看有趣的漫画
He reads the funny papers.
嗯...
Uh...
我想让你安排一个电话接线员
I want you to arrange to have a telephone man
检查所有进出这里的电话...
check all the calls that go in and out of here...
-我已经做了, 爸爸  -任何人都有可能
-I did it already, Pop.  -Could be anyone.
-我已经处理好了  -哦, 没错. 我忘了
-I took care of that. -Oh, that's right. I forgot.
怎么回事?
What's the matter?
什么事困扰着你?
What's bothering you?
我应付得了. 我告诉过你我能应付, 我会应付
I'll handle it. I told you I can handle it, I'll handle it.
我知道桑蒂诺会染指家族事业
I knew that Santino was gonna have to go through all this.
还有弗雷多...
and Fredo...
弗雷多他...
Fredo was...
但我从来... 从来没想让你参与
But I never... I never wanted this for you.
我干了一辈子. 我不道歉
I worked my whole life. I don't apologize
我照顾了我的家人
to take care of my family.
我拒绝做一个傻瓜
And I refused to be a fool
在那些大人物牵着的绳子上跳舞
dancing on a string held by all those big shots.
我不道歉. 这就是我的生活. 但我认为…
I don't apologize. That's my life. But I thought that...
这是你的时代, 你会是那个牵着绳子的人
That when it was your time,
that you would be the one to hold the strings.
柯里昂参议员
Senator Corleone.
柯里昂州长, 之类的
Governor Corleone. Something.
另一个大人物
Another pezzonovante.
这个...
Well...
只是时间不够, 迈克尔. 时间不够了
Just wasn't enough time, Michael. Wasn't enough time.
我们会做到的, 爸爸
We'll get there, Pop.
-我们会做到的  -嗯
-We'll get there. -Hmm.
你听好
Now listen
不管是谁来找你跟巴西尼见面
whoever comes to you with this Barzini meeting
他就是叛徒
he's the traitor.
别忘了这一点
Don't forget that.
我能自己浇水
Can I water these.
-我可以浇水吗?  -可以
-Can I water these? -Yeah.
浇吧
That's fine.
这里. 浇这里
Over here. Over here.
小心点, 你把它洒了
Be careful. You're spilling it.
安东尼, 过来, 过来
Anthony, come here, come here.
过来
Come here.
对了. 我们把它放在这儿
That's right. We'll put it right there.
我给你看样东西
I'll show you something.
过来, 过来
Come here, come here.
你站好了
Now, you stand there.
把橙子给我!
Give me an orange!
这是新戏法
That's a new trick.
你跑进去. 快跑进去
You run in there. Run in there.
-你在哪儿?  -谁?
-Where are you? -Who?
倒下!
Ouch!
迈克, 能借一步说话吗?
Mike, can I have a minute?
巴西尼想要安排一次会议
Barzini wants to arrange a meeting.
他说任何问题都可以谈出一个解决之道
He says we can straighten any of our problems out.
-你和他谈过了?  -是的
-You talked to him? -Yeah.
我可以安排保护措施
I can arrange security.
在我的地盘上. 好吗?
On my territory. All right?
-好  -好的
-All right. -All right.
你知道他们会怎么对付你吗?
Do you know how they're gonna come at you?
他们正在布鲁克林安排一次会议
They're arranging a meeting in Brooklyn.
泰西欧的地盘
Tessio's ground.
说在那儿我会很安全
where I'll be safe.
我一直以为是克莱门扎, 没想到是泰西欧
I always thought it would've been Clemenza, not Tessio.
这一招漂亮. 泰西欧一向聪明
It's the smart move. Tessio was always smarter.
但我要等
But I'm gonna wait.
等洗礼过了再说
After the baptism.
我决定当康妮孩子的教父了
I've decided to be godfather to Connie's baby.
然后我去见巴西尼阁下
And then I'll meet with Don Barzini
还有塔塔基利亚
and Tattaglia.
所有五大家族的族长
All the heads of the five families.
(意大利语祷词)
阿门
Amen.
(意大利语祷词)
迈克尔, 你相信上帝
Michael, do you believe in God
全能的天父, 天地的创造者吗?
the Father Almighty creator of Heaven and Earth?
我相信
I do.
你相信耶稣基督, 他唯一的儿子, 我们的主吗?
Do you believe in Jesus Christ, his only Son, our Lord?
我相信
I do.
你相信圣灵, 神圣的天主教会吗?
Do you believe in the holy Ghost, the holy Catholic Church?
我相信
I do.
(意大利语祷词)
迈克尔·弗朗西斯·里兹
Michael Francis Rizzi
你放弃了撒旦吗?
do you renounce Satan?
我声明放弃了他
I do renounce him.
他所有的作为吗?
And all his works?
我确实放弃了它们
I do renounce them.
还有他所有的浮华?
And all his pomps?
我确实放弃了它们
I do renounce them.
迈克尔·里兹
Michael Rizzi
你愿意接受洗礼吗?
will you be baptized?
我愿意
I will.
(意大利语祷词)
迈克尔·里兹, 平静地走吧
Michael Rizzi, go in peace.
愿主与你同在. 阿门
And may the Lord be with you. Amen.
凯!
Kay!
亲吻你的教父
Kiss your godfather.
-卡洛 -什么事?
-Carlo. -What?
不能去拉斯维加斯了
Can't go to Vegas.
出了点事, 每个人都得离开, 除了我们
Something's come up. Everybody has to leave without us.
-哦, 迈克, 这是我们第一次一起度假 -康妮, 别吵
-Oh, Mike, it's our first vacation together. -Connie, please.
-你要我怎么做?  -回家去等我电话, 有重要的事
-What do you wanna do?
-Go back to the house. Wait for my call. It's important.
好的
All right
我只去几天
I'll only be a couple of days.
旅途愉快, 妈妈
Have a nice trip, Mama.
我们在去布鲁克林的路上
We're on our way to Brooklyn.
我希望迈克今晚能给我们一笔好交易
I hope Mike can get us a good deal tonight.
我相信会的
I'm sure he will.
萨尔, 汤姆
Sal, Tom
老板说他会单独坐一辆车来
the boss says he'll come in a separate car.
他说让你们俩先走
He says for you two to go on ahead.
他不能那么做
He can't do that.
-它打乱了我所有的安排  -他是这么说的
-It screws up all my arrangements. -That's what he said.
我也不能去, 萨尔
I can't go either, Sal.
告诉迈克这纯粹是生意
Tell Mike it was only business.
我一直都喜欢他
I always liked him.
他明白这一点
He understands that.
抱歉, 萨尔
Excuse me, Sal.
汤姆, 能帮我求个情吗?
Tom, Can you get me off the hook?
-看在老交情的份上 -我做不到, 萨尔
-For old times' sake. -Can't do it, Sally.
你得为桑蒂诺的死偿命, 卡洛
You have to answer for Santino, Carlo.
-迈克, 你完全搞错了 -你为巴西尼的人设计害了桑尼
Mike, you got it all wrong.
-You fingered Sonny for the Barzini people.
啊, 你和我姐姐演的那场小闹剧
Ah, that little farce you played with my sister.
以为骗得过柯里昂家的人吗?
Did you think that could fool a Corleone?
迈克, 我是清白的
Mike, I'm innocent.
我以孩子的名义发誓
I swear on the kids.
-求你, 迈克, 别这样对我 -坐下
-Please, Mike, don't do this to me. -Sit down.
别这样对我, 求你了
Don't do this to me, please.
巴西尼死了
Barzini's dead.
菲利普·塔塔基利亚也死了
So is Phillip Tattaglia.
还有莫·格林, 斯特拉奇, 库尼奥
Moe Greene, Strachi, Cuneo.
今天我要解决所有家族事务
Today I settle all family business
所以别跟我说你是无辜的, 卡洛
so don't tell me you're innocent, Carlo.
承认你所做过的
Admit what you did.
给他拿杯喝的
Get him a drink.
说吧
Come on.
别害怕, 卡洛
Don't be afraid, Carlo.
你以为我会让我姐姐当寡妇吗?
You think I'd make my sister a widow?
我又是你儿子的教父, 卡洛
I'm godfather to your son, Carlo.
喝吧, 喝吧
Go ahead, drink, drink.
卡洛, 从此你退出家族的生意. 这是给你的惩罚
No, Carlo. you're out of the family business. That's your punishment.
你玩完了. 我送你上飞机去拉斯维加斯
You're finished. I'm putting you on a plane to Vegas.
汤姆
Tom.
-我要你留在那边. 明白吗?  -嗯嗯
-I want you to stay there. Understand? -Mmm-hmm.
只是别告诉我你是无辜的
Only don't tell me you're innocent.
因为这侮辱了我的智商
because it insults my intelligence.
这让我很生气
It makes me very angry.
告诉我, 是谁找的你?
Now, who approached you?
塔塔基利亚还是巴西尼?
Tattaglia or Barzini?
是巴西尼
It was Barzini.
好
Good.
外面有辆车在等着你, 会送你去机场
There's a car waiting for you outside to take you to the airport.
我会给你妻子打电话, 告诉她你坐的是哪班飞机
I'll call your wife, tell her what flight you're on.
-迈克...  -滚出我的视线
-Mike... -Get out of my sight.
你好, 卡洛
Hello, Carlo.
你能不能别哭了? 你想告诉我什么?
Will you stop crying? What are you trying to tell me?
-我告诉你你错了 -妈妈, 求你了!
-I'm telling you you're wrong. -Oh, Mama, please!
迈克尔! 迈克尔!
Michael! Michael!
-怎么了?  -他在哪儿? 迈克尔!
-What is it? -Where is he? Michael!
麦克, 你这混蛋! 你杀了我丈夫!
Michael, you lousy bastard! You killed my husband!
你一直等到爸爸去世, 没人能管你了
You waited until Papa died so nobody could stop you
所以你就把他杀了!
and then you killed him!
你把桑尼的死怪在他头上
You blamed him for Sonny.
你一直都这样, 大家都这样
You always did. Everybody did.
但你从来没有想过我!
But you never thought about me!
你根本就不在乎我!
You never gave a damn about me!
我以后要怎么办?
Now what am I gonna do?
康妮
Connie.
你以为他为什么把卡洛留在他身边?
Why do you think he kept Carlo at the mall?
他一直都知道他会杀了他
All the time he knew he was gonna kill him.
你还是我们孩子的教父
And you stood godfather to our baby.
你这个卑鄙无情的混蛋
You lousy, coldhearted bastard.
想知道除了卡洛, 他同时还杀了多少人吗?
Want to know how many men he had killed with Carlo?
看看报纸吧! 看看报纸吧!
Read the papers! Read the papers!
那就是你丈夫! 那就是你丈夫!
That's your husband! That's your husband!
不要! 不要, 不...
No! No, no...
带她上楼
Take her upstairs.
-给她找个医生  -哦, 上帝!
-Get her a doctor. -Oh, God!
她歇斯底里了
She's hysterical.
歇斯底里
Hysterical.
迈克尔, 这是真的吗?
Michael, is it true?
-别过问我的生意, 凯 -这是真的吗?
-Don't ask me about my business, Kay. -Is it true?
别过问我的生意
Don't ask me about my business.
-不  -够了!
-No -Enough!
好吧
All right.
就这一次
This one time.
就这一次, 我让你过问我的公事
This one time, I'll let you ask me about my affairs.
这是真的吗?
Is it true?
不是
No.
我想我们两个都需要喝一杯, 是吧?
I guess we both need a drink, huh?
我去倒
Come on.
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone.
字幕整理修订：北京老刘 2023.3.27